<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A fannatick's testimony against swearing; being an ansvver to four books, published by John Tombes, Jeremiah Ives, and Theophilus Brabourne; but more especially to that by Henry Den. By Henry Adis, a baptized believer, undergoing the name of a free-willer; and also most ignomineously by the tongue of infamy, called a fannatick, or a mad man.</title>
            <author>Adis, Henry.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75886</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A583</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1084_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36719</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872460</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872460</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169357</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75886)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169357)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 161:E1084[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A fannatick's testimony against swearing; being an ansvver to four books, published by John Tombes, Jeremiah Ives, and Theophilus Brabourne; but more especially to that by Henry Den. By Henry Adis, a baptized believer, undergoing the name of a free-willer; and also most ignomineously by the tongue of infamy, called a fannatick, or a mad man.</title>
                  <author>Adis, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>50, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by S. Dover, in Martins Le Grand, near Aldersgate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Primarily a reply to: Denne, Henry.  An epistle recommended to all the prisons in the city &amp; nation.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "march 2d", "1660"; imprint date crossed through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ives, Jeremiah, fl. 1653-1674.</term>
               <term>Tombes, John, 1603?-1676.</term>
               <term>Brabourne, Theophilus, b. 1590.</term>
               <term>Denne, Henry, 1606 or 7-1660? --  Epistle recommended to all the prisons in the city &amp; nation.</term>
               <term>Oaths --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169357:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Fannatick's Teſtimony AGAINST SWEARING; Being An ANSVVER TO FOUR BOOKS, Publiſhed by <hi>John Tombes, Jeremiah Ives,</hi> and <hi>Theophilus Brabourne;</hi> But more eſpecially to that by <hi>Henry Den.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>HENRY ADIS,</hi> a Baptized Believer, undergoing the Name of a Free-Willer; and alſo moſt ignomineouſly by the tongue of Infamy, called a <hi>Fannatick,</hi> or <hi>a mad man.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Above all things, my Brethren, Swear not, <bibl>
                  <hi>Jam. 5.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>For becauſe of Swearing the Land mourneth, <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer. 23.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>—But ſpeak the Truth every man to his Neighbour— <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 4.25.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>And lye not one to another, ſeeing ye have put off the old man with his deeds, <bibl>
                  <hi>Col. 3.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>And</hi> ſo ſpeak ye, and ſo do, as thoſe that ſhall be judged by the Law of Liberty, <bibl>
                  <hi>Jam. 2.12.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>S. Dover,</hi> in <hi>Martins Le Grand,</hi> near <hi>Alderſgate.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:169357:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:169357:2"/>
            <head>A Fannaticks Teſtimony AGAINST SVVEARING.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Henry Den,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THou in the back-ſide of thy Title Page of thy <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> ſpeakeſt ſomething of the <hi>deplorable Condition of Thouſands of honeſt, quiet, peaceable People, that have been driven by Troops into Priſon-Holes, both in Cities and Countries</hi> (the which <hi>England</hi> never ſaw the like before) And all this occaſioned by that late <hi>Fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, Wicked,</hi> and <hi>Bloudy Inſurrection,</hi> which occaſioned the Miniſters of Juſtice <hi>(though contrary to all Juſtice, Equity, and good Conſcience)</hi> to Execute <hi>their Pleaſures</hi> (not Juſtice) upon theſe Perſons, the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency of whom</hi> (as thou ſayeſt) <hi>hath appeared many wayes,</hi> as well by the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of the <hi>dying Offenders,</hi> as by their <hi>own Proteſtations;</hi> and the <hi>Confeſſion of thoſe men that would be glad to find occaſion againſt them, but are not able; neither</hi> will they <hi>in any thing, ſave in the things pertaining to the Worſhip of their God:</hi> Yet, ſayeſt thou, They are kept in <hi>Bonds as with a ſnare,</hi> which at this day, <hi>holds them in,</hi> and <hi>ſhuts the Priſon Doors</hi> againſt them; in that they (as thou ſayeſt) are taught, <hi>That it is not lawful upon any Occaſion,</hi> or before <hi>any Perſon to take an Oath;</hi> inſomuch that when the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance to the KING is tendered to many</hi> who are at <hi>Liberty,</hi> they <hi>rather chuſe <hi>Impriſonment,</hi> than to take an <hi>Oath;</hi>
               </hi> and many who are <hi>in Priſon, and have <hi>Liberty</hi> proffered</hi> upon <hi>Condition of taking the <hi>Oath,</hi>
               </hi> do <hi>rather chuſe to <hi>con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inue there,</hi> than purchaſe their Libertiy with <hi>ſwearing.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:169357:3"/>
            <p>And that all may <hi>prevent</hi> the <hi>impendent evil Conſequences neceſſarily following:</hi> Thou ſayeſt in <hi>Page</hi> 3. That thou wilt <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>lawfulneſs of an Oath</hi> in a <hi>ſerious and weighty Matter, which cannot otherwiſe be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And in the next place (thou ſayeſt) thou wilt <hi>Anſwer</hi> thoſe <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections,</hi> which are the <hi>Pillars</hi> that uphold the <hi>negative part.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In all which, that thou haſt hitherto ſaid, I cannot but <hi>commend</hi> thee, as once <hi>John</hi> the Revelator did thoſe <hi>Seven Churches</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> Rev. 2. <hi>and</hi> Rev. 3. Becauſe thou haſt ſaid that which is <hi>really true,</hi> as to the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency</hi> of that great number <hi>Impriſoned;</hi> yet give me leave in the words of the ſame <hi>John,</hi> to let thee know, That there are a <hi>few things againſt thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt, Becauſe that in <hi>Page</hi> 3. thou ſpeakeſt that which is not altogether true; in ſaying, <hi>That an Oath is nothing elſe but a Religious Promiſe made in the preſence of the living God,</hi> whom (ſayeſt thou) <hi>we <hi>call to witneſs</hi> the truth of our words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which <hi>Aſſertion</hi> thou wouldeſt (if poſſible) beget Perſons to a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, that if <hi>a man call one to Witneſs a thing,</hi> that ſuch a calling to Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is <hi>a Swearing by that Perſon</hi> whom we ſo call to Witneſs: As if <hi>John Tombs</hi> ſhould make <hi>Henry Den</hi> a <hi>Religious Promiſe,</hi> to Preach at their Meeting at ſuch a time, and call <hi>Henry Adis</hi> to Witneſs this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe; will <hi>Henry Den</hi> dare to ſay, that <hi>John Tombs</hi> did <hi>SWEAR</hi> by <hi>Henry Adis,</hi> when <hi>John Tombs</hi> only called <hi>Henry Adis</hi> to <hi>WIT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESS?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>John Tombs, Henry Den,</hi> or <hi>Henry Adis,</hi> either or all of them may Safely, Honeſtly, or upon a good Accompt ſay, and that without fraud, that ſuch a Promiſe was made, and that ſuch an one was Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to that Promiſe.</p>
            <p>And further, if <hi>calling,</hi> or <hi>ſetting up a Witneſs</hi> be a <hi>Swearing</hi> by that <hi>Witneſs,</hi> then <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Laban</hi> Swore; <hi>Jacob</hi> by the <hi>Pillar of Stone,</hi> and that <hi>heap of Stones,</hi> Gen. 31.45. to 49. And I ſhall Appeal to the Judgment of any rational man, to judge, whether <hi>Laban,</hi> in verſ. 49. did <hi>Swear by the Lord,</hi> when he ſaid, The Lord ſhall <hi>Watch between us?</hi> Or, whether he Swore by the Lord in <hi>verſ.</hi> 50. when he ſaid, the Lord is <hi>Witneſs between us?</hi> Any more than he, and <hi>Jacob Swore</hi> by the heap of Stones, when they ſaid, <hi>This Heap ſhall be a Witneſs:</hi> And whether the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>Swear by the Lord,</hi> when he calls God to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, or Witneſs? 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23. and <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.8. any more then <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Laban SWORE by the Heap of Stones,</hi> as aforeſaid. Or, whether <hi>Moſes Swore</hi> by <hi>the Song of Deliverance,</hi> when he ſaid, That that Song ſhould be a <hi>Witneſs</hi> againſt <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Deut. 31.19, 21.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169357:3"/>
            <p>But I need not ſay more to this, for notwithſtanding in <hi>Page</hi> 3. thou doſt affirm, that an Oath is <hi>nothing elſe</hi> but <hi>a calling God to witneſs, &amp;c.</hi> Yet in <hi>Page</hi> 5. thou telleſt us, that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty matters, frequently uſed Expreſſions <hi>equal to an Oath,</hi> as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.9. where he ſaith, <hi>God is my witneſs, &amp;c.</hi> So that in one <hi>Page</hi> thou telleſt us, That <hi>calling God to witneſs,</hi> is <hi>Equal to an Oath;</hi> And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Page</hi> thou telleſt us, That an Oath is nothing elſe but a calling God to Witneſs.</p>
            <p>And ſo doth thy Brother <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> deal with us, He telleth us in his Book, <hi>Page</hi> 6. poſitively what an Oath is, from <hi>Gen.</hi> 23.4. when <hi>Abraham</hi> cauſed his Servant to Swear <hi>BY the Lord.</hi> And <hi>David</hi> Sware to <hi>Saul BY the Lord,</hi> 1 Sam. 21.23. And the <hi>Spies</hi> Swore <hi>BY the Lord</hi> to <hi>Rahab,</hi> Joſh. 2.12. And <hi>Abraham</hi> Swore <hi>BY the Lord</hi> to <hi>Abimelech, Gen.</hi> 21.13.</p>
            <p>And yet in <hi>Page</hi> 10. he Aſſerteth under his <hi>Fourth Reaſon</hi> that he giveth, Why Swearing is lawful, now under a Goſpel Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; he Aſſerteth, that a Calling God to witneſs is a Swearing; and yet when he hath Aſſerted it, then he comes and tells us, that if cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling God to witneſs be not Swearng, he ſaith, he knows not what is; when in <hi>Page</hi> 6. he did ſhew what was Swearing.</p>
            <p>For <hi>John Tombs</hi> and <hi>Henry Den,</hi> may both wear <hi>Black Coats,</hi> and have <hi>humane Learning,</hi> and both may be <hi>very like one another</hi> (as is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed they are in other things alſo) and may both <hi>write in and about one and the ſame Oathes,</hi> as they do; yet <hi>Henry Den</hi> and <hi>John Tombs</hi> are not <hi>one <hi>in them,</hi>
               </hi> although they both <hi>aim at one and the ſame End <hi>by them:</hi>
               </hi> And I Query, Whether the Learning ye ſpeak by, be the Spirits Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates, becauſe ye ſpeak not the Spirits Language, which is not <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi> but <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen</hi> in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I would I knew where to find you;</hi> yet by this I ſee, when perſons be out of Gods way, they begin to be in a bewildred Condition, running to and fro, ſometimes <hi>here,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>there;</hi> and therefore I muſt let thee know that every <hi>like</hi> is not the <hi>ſame;</hi> for another man may wear <hi>Black Cloaths,</hi> and be endowed with <hi>Humane Learning</hi> as well as <hi>Henry Den,</hi> yet not be <hi>Henry Den.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeeing it is ſo, that many are at a ſtumble in this juncture of time, as to <hi>taking,</hi> or <hi>not taking</hi> of OATHS; and that chiefly occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the <hi>Writings</hi> of <hi>John Tombs,</hi> thine <hi>Epiſtle,</hi> and thy Brother <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah Ives</hi> his <hi>Great Caſe of Conſcience Opened:</hi> I ſhall therefore en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour by <hi>divine Aſſiſtance, according to the Ability received,</hi> to lay down ſomething to the ſerious Conſideration <hi>of All,</hi> nothing doubting but that the <hi>LORD, from whom every good and perfect Gift cometh, will
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169357:4"/> make bare his own Arm,</hi> and evidence his own <hi>Wiſdom, Strength,</hi> and <hi>Alſufficiency,</hi> in his Servants <hi>Folly, Weakneſſe</hi> and <hi>Inſufficiency,</hi> to the <hi>ſtrengthning</hi> thoſe that <hi>ſtand;</hi> to the <hi>enlightning the Eyes</hi> of the <hi>Blind;</hi> to the <hi>eſtabliſhing</hi> of the <hi>wavouring</hi> and <hi>unſtable,</hi> and to the <hi>recovering</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtatized Back-ſlider,</hi> even <hi>to the ſmiting upon the Thigb,</hi> that ſo the Crown may be ſet upon his head, who only and alone is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy.</p>
            <p>In order whereunto I ſhall plainly, and as briefly as I may, diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between,
<list>
                  <item>1. A Vow, Covenant, Promiſe, or Engagement.</item>
                  <item>2. An Aſſeveration.</item>
                  <item>3. An Oath.</item>
                  <item>4. A Teſtimony, Record, or Witneſs.</item>
                  <item>5. An Adjuration, Charging, Warning, or Conjuring by.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>And firſt of a Vow, Covenant, Promiſe, or Engagement.</head>
               <p>A <hi>Vow, Covenant, Promiſe,</hi> or <hi>Engagement</hi> then, is nothing elſe, but a <hi>Promiſe</hi> made either to <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>man;</hi> or, <hi>an opening the mouth by way of Engaging:</hi> for ſo ſaith <hi>Jephthah,</hi> Judg. 11.35, 36. <hi>I have opened my mouth to the Lord, and I cannot go back.</hi> And this, I ſay, may be done either to God or man, and ſo be diſtinguiſhed to be either <hi>Divine,</hi> or <hi>Humane;</hi> and that upon Conditions, or voluntarily and without Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; the which being paſſed, either to God or man, upon or with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Conditions, yet they are as ſo many Bonds to, or upon a ſoul.</p>
               <p>And this Bond may be more ſtrictly bound upon a ſoul, by way of <hi>Oath, Curſe,</hi> or <hi>Execration,</hi> as ſhall be more fully ſhown hereafter. In order whereunto; firſt, conſider Voluntary Vows, Covenants, Promiſes, or Engagements.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Voluntary,</hi> as <hi>Davids</hi> Vow, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.2. who <hi>vowed a Vow to the mighty God of Jacob.</hi> But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Conditional,</hi> as <hi>Jacobs</hi> Vow, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.20. And <hi>Jacob vewed a Vow unto the Lord, and ſaid, If the Lord ſhall without fail do thus for me, then will I do</hi> ſo and ſo.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Jephthahs Vow,</hi> Judg. 11.30. <hi>And Jephthah vowed a Vow unto the Lord, and ſaid, If thou ſhalt without fail deliver the Children of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon into my hands, then it ſhall be, that whatſoever cometh forth of the door of my houſe, to meet me when I return in peace from the Children of</hi> Ammon, <hi>ſhall ſurely be the Lords, I will offer it up for a Burnt-Offering.</hi> And <hi>Hannah</hi> vowed a <hi>Conditional Vow,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.11. All theſe Vows were without an Oath.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:169357:4"/>
               <p>And all ſuch <hi>Vows,</hi> whether Conditional or Voluntary, yet they are as ſo many <hi>Bonds to the Soul,</hi> as in <hi>Num.</hi> 30.3. If a woman <hi>vow a Vow unto the Lord, <hi>to bind her ſoul with a bond,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp;c. any ſuch <hi>Vow, Covenant,</hi> or <hi>Promiſe</hi> may be further bound upon a foul with an Oath, as in <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.2. <hi>If a man vow a Vow unto the Lord,</hi> or <hi>ſwear an Oath, to <hi>bind his ſoul with a bond;</hi>
                  </hi> So that he that maketh a <hi>Vow, Covenant,</hi> or <hi>Promiſe, bindeth his ſoul with a bond:</hi> and he that ſweareth an <hi>Oath,</hi> to <hi>perform</hi> that Vow, Covenant, or Promiſe, bindeth his ſoul <hi>with a double bond;</hi> So that every Oath is a Vow; becauſe that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not properly be made, but to perform ſomething that is vowed, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, covenanted, or engaged; and ſo the Oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h includeth that thing ſo promiſed to perform it, and ſo becomes one with it; for break the Oath, when once ſworn, and break the Vow or Engagement; perform the Oath, and the Engagement is made good. Yet every Vow is not an Oath, becauſe it may be made without an Oath, as in <hi>Jacobs, Jephthahs,</hi> and <hi>Hannahs</hi> Vows, which were <hi>Vows without Oaths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And we find where Vows are made with Oaths, they are generally ſo diſtinguiſhed, as in <hi>Numb.</hi> 30.2. <hi>If a man vow a Vow unto the Lord, or ſwear an Oath to bind his ſoul with a bond, &amp;c.</hi> So likewiſe in <hi>Davids</hi> caſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132.1, 2. <hi>Lord, remember</hi> David <hi>in all his troubles, how he ſware unto the Lord, and vowed a Vow unto the mighty God of Jacob:</hi> So that here it is diſtinctly laid down how he <hi>ſware unto the Lord,</hi> and <hi>vowed a Vow;</hi> intimating a double tye or bond upon his ſoul, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid.</p>
               <p>The like we may ſee in <hi>Iſraels</hi> caſe, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.12. <hi>And they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into a Covenant to ſeek the Lord God of their Fathers, with all their heart, and with all their ſoul:</hi> this Covenant was a <hi>bond to their ſouls.</hi> And in verſe 14. <hi>They <hi>ſware</hi> unto the Lord with a loud voice, and with Trumpets, and with Cornets: And all</hi> Judah <hi>rejoyced at the <hi>Oath;</hi> for they had <hi>ſworn</hi> with all their heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like alſo we may ſee in <hi>Nehem.</hi> 10.29. <hi>They clave unto their Brethren, their Nobles, and <hi>entered</hi> into a <hi>Curſe,</hi> and <hi>into an Oath,</hi> to walk in Gods Laws.</hi> To walk in Gods Laws was the Covenant, as you may read, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.38. <hi>This was written and ſealed to:</hi> And the <hi>Oath,</hi> and the <hi>Curſe, was entred into to perform that Covenant.</hi> So that we ſee they bound their ſouls with a <hi>double B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi> And by what hath been ſaid it may appear, that a <hi>Vow, Covenant,</hi> or <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and an <hi>Oath,</hi> are two diſtinct things.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing it is ſo then, that Vows, Covenants and Engagements are not Oaths, nor Swearing; this then may ſerve to ſet a period to that common ſaying, <hi>That Swearing is lawful under the Gospel,</hi> becauſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169357:5"/> the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was under a Vow, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.18. and <hi>Act.</hi> 21.23.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>2. An <hi>Aſſeveration.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>But, ſecondly, <hi>Every Aſſeveration is not an Oath,</hi> though <hi>every Oath is an Aſſeveration.</hi> An Aſſeveration then is, when a perſon ſhall <hi>chuſe out, ſever,</hi> or <hi>ſet apart</hi> a perſon or thing that is <hi>certain</hi> and <hi>known to be,</hi> and ſhall <hi>aſſert the certainty of ſomething elſe</hi> by the <hi>certainty</hi> of that <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain thing.</hi> I ſay, an <hi>Aſſeveration</hi> then is, when a perſon ſhall aſſert a thing to be a ttuth, or ſuch or ſuch a thing to be ſo, or not ſo, taking up ſome <hi>certain thing</hi> to <hi>aſſert</hi> the truth of that <hi>Negation</hi> or <hi>Affirmation;</hi> endeavouring thereby to beget the party or parties ſpoken to, to a <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the thing ſo aſſerted,</hi> to be a truth: the which for Illuſtration-ſake we will ſuppoſe thus; <hi>Henry Den</hi> telleth <hi>Henry Adis,</hi> that ſuch a thing is <hi>true, <hi>as ſure</hi>
                  </hi> as <hi>Henry Adis <hi>liveth.</hi>
                  </hi> Now can <hi>Henry Adis</hi> honeſtly or ſenſibly ſay, that <hi>Henry Den</hi> did <hi>ſwear</hi> by <hi>Henry Adis,</hi> when he only <hi>aſſerted the truth of the thing, by that which</hi> Henry Adis <hi>ſenſibly knew was true and certain:</hi> And what difference is there if <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Den</hi> had ſaid to <hi>Henry Adis,</hi> that the thing was true, as <hi>ſure as the Lord liveth?</hi> the certainty of whoſe living no rational man will in the leaſt queſtion. And in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.18. where the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> doth affirm, that his preaching to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> was not <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Nay,</hi> but <hi>Yea</hi> and <hi>Amen:</hi> And to beget them to a belief of the truth of what he ſaid herein, he tells them, <hi>it is true,</hi> as <hi>ſure as the Lord is true.</hi> Now I ſhall leave it to the judgment of the Rational to determine, whether the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> did ſwear <hi>by the Lord,</hi> any more than <hi>Henry Den</hi> did ſwear by <hi>Henry Adis,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>3. Of an <hi>Oath.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>But, thirdly, Had <hi>Henry Den</hi> told <hi>Henry Adis</hi> that ſuch a thing had been true, and had aſſerted the truth of it, <hi>by <hi>the Lord,</hi> by <hi>Heaven,</hi> by <hi>Earth,</hi> by <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by <hi>his Head,</hi>
                  </hi> or <hi>by</hi> what elſe you will ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: this <hi>Henry Den,</hi> and <hi>Henry Adis</hi> both may poſitively affirm to be <hi>Swearing;</hi> And this I can own to be Swearing, although I do not aſſert the Swearing by <hi>Heaven, Earth, Jeruſalem,</hi> or <hi>the Head,</hi> to be lawful Oaths; no, nor ſwearing <hi>by God</hi> neither under a Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſation. I ſay it is the term <hi>By,</hi> that maketh the Aſſeveration, or thing <hi>ſevered, ſingled out, ſet apart,</hi> or <hi>aſſerted,</hi> to become an Oath.</p>
               <p>I deſire to be held excuſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f I give not (for want of Humane Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) thoſe proper diſtinctions and denominations to words, as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly they may deſerve in ſuch or ſuch places: for I profeſs ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly I know not the difference between a Particle, as it is ſo called, nor where or in what places they are to ſtand; or how or when they are to be ſo called; only I ſhall deſire, for Information-ſake, to impart
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169357:5"/> what in mercy is made out to me, for the Information and Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of others; therefore take my honeſt down-right meaning, and the Lord make it uſeful.</p>
               <p>I ſay, that which binds up all, is, the term <hi>By,</hi> which <hi>By</hi> is that which maketh an Aſſertion to <hi>become an Oath;</hi> for it is the Affirmation of a thing not yet believed to be a truth, by the certainty of that which is a truth, and is ſet apart, choſen out, ſevered or aſſerted; and <hi>by the certainty of it,</hi> to prove the certainty of that which is not yet believed to be true or certain, as aforeſaid: For to ſay, <hi>the Lord liveth,</hi> is not to ſwear by the living Lord, or by the Lord that liveth; nor to ſay, <hi>as true as the Lord liveth,</hi> cannot be ſwearing by the Lord that is true who liveth: but if I ſay, <hi>By the Lord that liveth,</hi> then I ſwear: So that to name <hi>God, Heaven, Earth,</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> is, nor can be Swearing, until I uſe the term <hi>By,</hi> as aforeſaid.</p>
               <p>And this thou ſayeſt thy ſelf <hi>is Swearing,</hi> in <hi>pag.</hi> 4. where thou ſpeakeſt of the univerſality of Oaths, in which thou ſayeſt muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, both <hi>perſons, places</hi> and <hi>times;</hi> and in the conſideration of <hi>perſons,</hi> thou bringeſt us, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.16. where the Lord ſweareth to <hi>Abraham,</hi> ſaying, <hi>By <hi>my Self have I ſworn,</hi> ſaith the Lord, That in bleſſing I will bleſſe thee:</hi> and in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89.35. <hi>Once have I ſworn <hi>by</hi> my Holineſſe, that I will not lye unto David:</hi> And the Angel's ſwearing in <hi>Revel.</hi> 10.5, 6. who lifted up his hands to Heaven, and ſaid, <hi>not as ſure as the Lord liveth,</hi> or, I <hi>call the Lord that liveth to record,</hi> or to <hi>witneſſe;</hi> but his ſwearing was on this wiſe, <hi>The Angel lifted up his hand to Heaven, and ſware <hi>by</hi> Him that liveth for ever and ever.</hi> And in <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.13. <hi>Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God, and ſerve Him, and ſhalt <hi>ſwear by his Name.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>To Swear then, is to Aſſert <hi>by</hi> God, who only is <hi>able</hi> to Aſſiſt, or <hi>enable</hi> to what is Promiſed; therefore it is unlawful to Swear BY any other Creature or Thing, becauſe that Creature is <hi>unable</hi> to <hi>enable</hi> the Creature. And 2dly, by ſo doing, the Creature is ſet up in the Place of the all-Powerful God; &amp; the Party ſo Swearing becomes an Idolater.</p>
               <p>And thou alſo affirmeſt this to be Swearing by a third Teſtimony, as from the Prophets, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.16. <hi>And he that ſweareth in the Earth, ſhall ſwear by the God of Truth.</hi> And <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Men verily ſwear <hi>by</hi> the Greater.</hi> So that to ſwear, is to aſſert <hi>by</hi> a party or thing, ſevered, ſingled out, or ſet apart. And of Oaths there are ſeveral kinds.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. An Oath of Promiſe.</item>
                  <item>2. An Oath of Affirmation or Teſtimony.</item>
                  <item>3. An Oath of Abjuration, to renounce or forſwear.</item>
                  <item>4. An Oath of Execration or Curſing.</item>
               </list>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:169357:6"/>1. All Promiſary Oaths are, when perſons do <hi>vow, covenant,</hi> or <hi>promiſe,</hi> and bind the performance thereof by or under an Oath; as <hi>Joſh.</hi> 2.12. <hi>Now therefore I pray you, ſwear unto me <hi>by the Lord,</hi> ſince I have ſhewed you kindneſs, that ye will alſo ſhew kindneſs unto my fathers houſe; and give me a true token.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. An Oath of Affirmation or Teſtimony, to Confirm a Truth, by way of Evidence, or Witneſs-bearing to end Controverſies, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16. <hi>For men verily Swear by the greater, and an Oath for Confirmation is to them an end of all ſtrife.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. An Oath of Abjuration, Renouncing, or Forſwearing a thing, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.35. <hi>And when all the People came to cauſe David to eat meat while it was yet day, David ſware, ſaying, So do God to me, and more alſo, if I taſte bread or ought elſe, till the Sun be down.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. An Oath of Execration or Curſing, <hi>Acts.</hi> 23.12, 14, 21. <hi>But do not thou yield un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o them; for there lie in wait for him of them more than forty men, which have bound themſelves with an Oath, that they will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eat nor drink till they have killed him; and now are they ready l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oking for a Promiſe from thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And although here is a New Teſtament Proof for this Oa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h of <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration,</hi> yet it is to be noted, that it was made by wicked men, and therefore no Example for Goſpel Diſciples to walk by, for 'tis the Requirement of the Lord by his Spirit, that we Regulate according to the Goſpel, which ſaith, <hi>Swear not,</hi> and <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> Matth. 5.35. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.12. And this we are required, that we regulate our <hi>Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as becometh the Goſpel, Phil.</hi> 1.27. Now if we have not a clear <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> in the Goſpel, to regulate our <hi>Converſation by,</hi> and in ſpecial in ſuch a <hi>principal Part of it as this is,</hi> that may <hi>ſo much concern the Glory of God;</hi> then we muſt conclude, that we are <hi>directed</hi> to an <hi>inſufficient and to an indirect Rule;</hi> the which to ſay I dare not: For I do really be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him to be faithful, who hath by his Spirit in his Servant <hi>directed to that Rule;</hi> and therefore I am of this perſwaſion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat the <hi>Rule is a <hi>direct Rule,</hi>
                  </hi> and a <hi>true meaſure,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.12. and that thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirements in <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th.</hi> 5.34. and <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.12. are <hi>poſitive Directions.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Of a Teſtimony, Record, <hi>or</hi> Witneſs.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fourthly,</hi> As to a Teſtimony, Record or Witneſs, I judge I need not ſay any thing to in this place, becauſe it is ſo fully diſtinguiſhed in <hi>Pag.</hi> 8. to be of <hi>another nature,</hi> &amp; not at all of the <hi>tendency</hi> of an Oath; for when <hi>I call one to witneſs</hi> a thing, <hi>I do not Swear by him;</hi> but I ſhall refer wholly to the aforeſaid <hi>Pages,</hi> &amp; ſhall proceed to what remains.</p>
               <p>And therefore ſhall deſire that <hi>John Tombs</hi> in ſeveral of his <hi>Pages,</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> in his <hi>Page</hi> 10. do lay theſe Scriptures, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.1.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169357:6"/> 
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.8. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.23. to their Pages as a ſufficient Anſwer to them, that the Apoſtle Swore not, any more than <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Laban,</hi> or <hi>John Tombs</hi> did Swear by <hi>Henry Adis,</hi> as is there cited.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Of an Adjuration, Charging, Warning, or Conjuring by.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fifthly,</hi> To Adjure, Charge, Warn, or Conjure, is <hi>no Swearing:</hi> As for Example, briefly thus; A Conſtable Commanding, Conjuring, Adjuring, or Charging another of the Kings Subjects in the Kings Name, or by the Kings Power or Authority, who is the Supream Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of the Nation, to Aid and Aſſiſt him in ſuch or ſuch a thing, in which he's ſo Charging, Adjuring, Conjuring or Warning; no man can ſenſibly ſay that he <hi>ſwears by the King:</hi> Yet there is an <hi>aw</hi> put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that <hi>Subject</hi> by the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> in <hi>Comanding or Adjuring in the Kings Name,</hi> or a Conjuring <hi>by the Power of the King,</hi> which that Subject is to <hi>Obey as he will anſwer the Neglect thereof at his peril:</hi> that is, if the King ſhould call <hi>him to <hi>queſtion</hi>
                  </hi> for his <hi>Neglect of that thing doing,</hi> poſſibly he muſt <hi>undergo the <hi>wrath</hi> of the KING, whoſe <hi>Wrath</hi> is as the Roaring of a Lion,</hi> Prov. 19.12. And <hi>as the Meſſenger of Death,</hi> Prov. 16.14.</p>
               <p>And that <hi>Command</hi> that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> laid upon the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> by the <hi>Lord Jeſus,</hi> That <hi>that Epiſtle be Read to all the Holy Brethren,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5.27. I judge the Apoſtle in <hi>reaſon, cannot he ſaid to SWEAR by the Lord Jeſus;</hi> but he lets them know, that he had <hi>an Authority to Require the <hi>reading</hi> of that Epiſtle,</hi> that as it was written by the <hi>Incommings</hi> of the <hi>Spirit of Jeſus,</hi> for the benefit <hi>of the Sheep of Jeſus;</hi> So he by the <hi>Authority</hi> of Jeſus, the great Shepherd and Biſhop of our Souls, required the <hi>reading of it; becauſe as he Aſcended up on High, ſo he had given Gifts unto men, for the <hi>perfecting of the Sain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> for the <hi>Work of the Miniſtry,</hi> for the <hi>edifying of the Body of Chriſt.</hi>
                  </hi> Eph. 4.8, 12. The which po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſibly may be done <hi>by Epiſtle at a diſtance,</hi> as well as <hi>by Preaching being preſent:</hi> And this is that which anſwers the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirement of Chriſt, that <hi>when we are Converted, that then we ſhould <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> the Brethren,</hi> Luk. 22.32. And alſo ſeconded by <hi>Peter</hi> in his Firſt Epiſtle, fourth Chapter, and the tenth Verſe, where he require<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h That as <hi>every man hath Received the Gift, ſo they ſhould <hi>miniſter the ſame one to another,</hi> as good Stewards of the manifold graces of God. And thus they ſhould feed the Sheep and Lambs of Jeſus,</hi> Joh. 21.14. And thus the Apoſtle <hi>Paul commends the things that he wrote unto them, to be the <hi>Commandements of the Lord,</hi>
                  </hi> 1 Cor. 14.34. For many things Chriſt had to ſay to his Diſciples, which they could not then bear, which were afterwards to be Communicated by the Spirit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.12, 13. According to that of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. <hi>For the Prophets came not of old time by the Will of Man, but Holy-men <hi>ſpake</hi> as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169357:7"/> they were <hi>moved by the holy Ghoſt;</hi>
                  </hi> and the <hi>ſame Spirit</hi> being the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>of this Epiſtle to the Church,</hi>
                  </hi> 1 Theſ. 5.27. <hi>Required in the Name of the Lord, or by the Power of the Lord, that it be Read to all the Holy Brethren.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the <hi>ſame Apoſtle,</hi> writing to the ſame Church, in <hi>perſwading</hi> them to a <hi>ſtedfaſtneſs</hi> in the way of God, he doth <hi>beſeech them BY the Coming of the Lord Jeſus, and BY our gathering together unto him, that they be not ſoon moved, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, can it be ſuppoſed that the Apoſtle <hi>did Swear</hi> when he <hi>Adjures them BY the coming of the Lord Jeſus;</hi> and <hi>BY our gathering together unto him?</hi> No, For if any one ſhall ſay he did, then he Swore <hi>not BY Chriſt only as he is Lord,</hi> but <hi>BY his coming,</hi> and <hi>BY our gathering together;</hi> the which, <hi>were Swearing lawful,</hi> to wit, <hi>BY the Lord,</hi> from <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. and <hi>James</hi> 5. <hi>Yet <hi>this</hi>
                  </hi> were to <hi>tranſgreſſe thoſe Lawes</hi> which ſay, <hi>Swear not BY Heaven, Earth,</hi> nor <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> nor <hi>BY any other <hi>Oath;</hi>
                  </hi> So that I ſay, if <hi>Swearing BY the Lord ſhould be <hi>lawful</hi> from thence,</hi> yet <hi>Swearing</hi> BY the <hi>Coming of the Lord;</hi> or BY <hi>our ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering together unto him,</hi> is <hi>utterly unlawful:</hi> So that to ſay that this faithful Servant of the Lords, whoſe great <hi>Care</hi> it was to keep the Churches <hi>cloſe to God;</hi> to ſay that he was thus a <hi>breaker of Gods Lawes,</hi> were, as I judge, to <hi>condemne the Innocent;</hi> which is a <hi>great Evil,</hi> and as great an abomination to the Lord, as he that juſtifieth the wicked, <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.15. The confounding of theſe <hi>Vowes, Oaths, Teſtimonies, Aſſeverations</hi> and <hi>Adjurations</hi> together, is that which cauſeth <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> in Page 3 and 7, to affirm that the Lord Chriſt <hi>SWARE, in ſaying, <hi>thou haſt ſaid it;</hi>
                  </hi> when the High Prieſt <hi>Adjured him BY the <hi>living God,</hi> that he ſhould tell him, whether he was the Chriſt,</hi> Matth. 26.63.</p>
               <p>And alſo that the Prophet <hi>Micha</hi> ſwore, when <hi>the King Adjured him BY</hi> or <hi>IN</hi> the <hi>Name of the Lord, to tell him nothing but the Truth: And they SWARE</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when they Conſented to Anſwer to that Voice of <hi>Swear,</hi>
                  </hi> 1 Kin. 22.16, 17. But I ſhall herein appeal to the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Rational, whether either the King, or the High Prieſt <hi>ſwore by the living God,</hi> when they Charged or Conjured <hi>BY</hi> or <hi>IN</hi> the <hi>Name of the living God;</hi> any more than the Conſtable Swears by the King, when he Commands <hi>by</hi> or <hi>in</hi> his Name? or whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her it can in reaſon be imagined that the Subjects do Swear BY the King, when they do actually Conſent to Obey the King in obeying his Conſtable, the Kings lawful Officer.</p>
               <p>Therefore in this Place, I hope I ſhall not need ſay more to theſe things, though more might be ſaid; as to Diſtinguiſh between a <hi>Vow,</hi> an <hi>Oath,</hi> an <hi>Aſſeveration,</hi> a <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> and an <hi>Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uration</hi> or <hi>Con ura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> ſo that an <hi>Adjruation</hi> is not a <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> nor a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> an
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169357:7"/> 
                  <hi>Adjuration;</hi> For when I call God to <hi>Witneſs,</hi> I do not <hi>adjure a perſon by the Lord, nor by Chriſts coming,</hi> nor by our <hi>gathering together unto him;</hi> neither <hi>when I do this, do I make a <hi>Vow,</hi>
                  </hi> or <hi>take an <hi>Oath</hi>
                  </hi> to perform that <hi>Vow;</hi> and on the other hand, when I make a <hi>Vow</hi> or a <hi>Covenant</hi> to, or with the Lord I do not <hi>adjure <hi>by the Lord,</hi>
                  </hi> for if I do, I would in reaſon know <hi>who I do <hi>adjure,</hi>
                  </hi> for I am the perſon <hi>Vowing,</hi> and I muſt be the party <hi>adjuring;</hi> and if that <hi>Covenant be with the Lord and my ſelf onely;</hi> then I muſt be ſaid, if I do <hi>adjure, to adjure the Lord by the Lord;</hi> the which to ſay, I ſhall leave to the rational to judge what it amounteth too: Thus much ſhall ſuffice to have been ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, as to diſtinguiſh between a <hi>Vow,</hi> an <hi>Oath,</hi> a <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> an <hi>Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veration,</hi> and an <hi>Adjuration.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now having thus diſtinguiſhed, I ſhall as briefly as I may, come to the remaining part of thy Epiſtle; And firſt, I ſhall ſay ſomething to that Text, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.16. in page 4. <hi>Men verily do Swear by the greater, and an Oath for confirmation, is to <hi>them</hi> an end of all ſtrife:</hi> which words the Apoſtle intendeth not to urge, or to perſwade to an opinion of the lawfulneſſe of Swearing, as <hi>Henry Den</hi> doth, nor need he, for it was that <hi>Church of the Jews,</hi> converted <hi>to the Faith, and Baptized</hi> into the <hi>Name of Jeſus, for the remiſſion of ſins,</hi> Acts 2.41. For as they were <hi>Jews,</hi> they were under that ſaying of old, <hi>Thou ſhalt fear the Lord thy God and ſerve him, and ſhalt Swear by his Name,</hi> who were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law of Chriſt, who out of his own Mouth ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and for that Apoſtle to bind ſo cloſe upon them, for a ſtrict obſervation of the Laws of Chriſt, as he doth, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1, 2, 3. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.25. and yet to bring this Text in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.13. to perſwade to <hi>a breach of that L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w,</hi> to me ſeems a <hi>Paradox;</hi> I ſhall therefore come to an examination of the <hi>end why thoſe words were ſpoken,</hi> that ſo if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly, we may be <hi>inſtrumental</hi> to <hi>undeceive one another;</hi> for to take a <hi>Text,</hi> and to make uſe of it as ſome do, <hi>for their own ends,</hi> and not to <hi>conſider the end, why that Text was ſpoken by the Spirit; is to go out of Gods way,</hi> and to <hi>perſwade others</hi> ſo to do <hi>and Devil</hi>-like, to <hi>pervert Scripture,</hi> to <hi>ſubvert Souls.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle in <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. earneſtly perſwades that <hi>Church</hi> to a preſſing on to <hi>perfection,</hi> being already built upon the <hi>foundation</hi> of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief corner ſtone:</hi>
                  </hi> In <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.12. a d ſo on, he blameth them for their <hi>backwardneſſe</hi> and <hi>ſlothfulneſſe in the Way of God;</hi> and <hi>blameth them</hi> for a <hi>neglect</hi> of that which the <hi>great Learned Rabbies of our times <hi>cries out againſt, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſons,</hi> and <hi>blames us</hi> for, now at this very day;</hi> that is, for <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:169357:8"/> And becauſe we are <hi>forward</hi> to follow God in his Requirements, to Aſſemble together, to build each other up in our moſt Holy Faith, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the direction of the Lord, by his Spirit, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25. <hi>Therefore</hi> our <hi>Meetings must be ſhut up,</hi> and we muſt be forced, not onely to neglect them, <hi>but alſo to Swear againſt them,</hi> or elſe we muſt be <hi>caſt into Dungeons, and Priſon-Holes, as it is at this day;</hi> my ſelf with many more can ſpeak it by <hi>woful experience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, the Apoſtle blaming them, for a carnal neglecting of that duty of <hi>teaching others,</hi> the which I cannot but mind by the way; <hi>he blames not thoſe that were <hi>already Teachers,</hi> for their <hi>negligence</hi> in <hi>Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi>
                  </hi> but he blameth thoſe <hi>of the Church,</hi> who for the time they had been <hi>in the Church, ought to have been <hi>Teachers of others,</hi> who had need to have others <hi>teach them again</hi> which are the <hi>firſt Principles of the Oracles of God;</hi>
                  </hi> and are become ſuch as have <hi>need</hi> of <hi>Milk,</hi> and not <hi>ſtrong Meat:</hi> Whence I would note by the way, <hi>that Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in Goſpel Churches, are not Taught to Teach in Vniverſities of Humane Learning, <hi>before</hi>
                  </hi> they <hi>come into their Societies;</hi> but in <hi>the Churches,</hi> they, after they have <hi>experienced</hi> the Love of God to their Souls, and have made uſe of the <hi>priviledges of the Gospel <hi>in the Church, to Propheſie one by one,</hi>
                  </hi> as they may do, <hi>that all may Learn, and all may be Comforted,</hi> 1 Cor. 14.31. Having, I ſay, blamed them for their <hi>careleſneſs</hi> and <hi>backwardneſs</hi> in <hi>inſtructing</hi> and <hi>Teaching</hi> others, they were alſo urged, to a <hi>preſſing</hi> on to <hi>perfection,</hi> or a <hi>building</hi> high upon that <hi>Foundation</hi> they had already laid; the <hi>Principles</hi> whereof are laid down, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2. to wit, <hi>Repentance, Faith</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm, Laying</hi> on of <hi>Hands,</hi> and to <hi>believe</hi> the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of <hi>the dead,</hi> and <hi>eternal Judgment;</hi> and that they might the more cheerfully go on in that way, he perſwadeth them in <hi>verſ.</hi> 12. That they be not <hi>ſloathful,</hi> but <hi>followers</hi> of them, who through <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Patience inherited the Promiſes;</hi> and that he might perſwade them yet further, he telleth them, that when God <hi>made Promiſe</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he could <hi>Swear</hi> by no <hi>greater,</hi> he <hi>Swore by Himſelf,</hi> ſaying, that in <hi>bleſsing, I will bleſs thee,</hi> and in <hi>multiplying,</hi> I will <hi>multiply</hi> thee.</p>
               <p>And further, he telleth them <hi>of Gods Swearing</hi> alſo, as to the ſetting <hi>Chriſt apart, a Prieſt for ever,</hi> after the <hi>Order of Melchiſedec;</hi> and upon theſe two accounts, the Apoſtle perſwadeth them to a <hi>perſeverance</hi> in Gods way, in <hi>certain hope</hi> of a reaping the <hi>benefit thereof in due time;</hi> and the better to perſwade them to a <hi>belief</hi> of the efficacy of <hi>Gods Oaths,</hi> he by a <hi>familiar compariſon, layes before them</hi> the <hi>effect</hi> of <hi>Mans Oaths <hi>in witneſs bearing;</hi>
                  </hi> And therefore he telleth them, <hi>that an
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169357:8"/> Oath amongſt men, for confirmation, is to them an end of all ſtrife;</hi> as much as if he ſhould have ſaid, if <hi>an Oath</hi> be of ſuch <hi>weight,</hi> and <hi>bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſo much ſway amongſt men, carnal, unbelieving, prophane wicked men, as generally men are</hi> (for they are <hi>either Carnal or Spiritual, belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving or unbelieving</hi>) then of what <hi>Credit</hi> ſhould <hi>Gods Oaths be off,</hi> for the <hi>confirmation of what he Sweareth to amongst you Chriſtians,</hi> to you <hi>Church of the Hebrews,</hi> with you that <hi>have owned,</hi> and are under the <hi>Principles of Chriſts Doctrine?</hi> for if we will mind the words, he telleth them of the uſe of an Oath amongſt men, conſidered as men, not of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> nor of <hi>Churches,</hi> but an Oath <hi>to them, <hi>not to you, but</hi> to them</hi> as they are men, ſuch as he wrote to them of, to them an Oath is an end of all ſtrife; not to you, neither is nor ſhall an Oath be, for confirmation an end of all ſtrife; but let your communication be <hi>Yea, Yea, Nay, Nay,</hi> for whatſoever is more then this, cometh of evil; for I ſay unto you. <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> So that he layeth it not down as a Rule for them to walk by; and therefore he telleth them, what an Oath <hi>to them</hi> is, ſo and ſo; he ſaith not, it ſhall be <hi>to you</hi> ſo and ſo; ſo that he layeth it not before them as a <hi>preſident</hi> or a <hi>pattern</hi> for them <hi>to follow,</hi> as to the <hi>practical part of it,</hi> but that they ſhould <hi>make the like uſe of <hi>Gods Oaths,</hi> as men do of one anothers <hi>Oaths,</hi>
                  </hi> that is, <hi>to put the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of doubt that is <hi>Sworn to;</hi>
                  </hi> Now God having Sworn to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and they being the <hi>Hebrew</hi> or <hi>Jewiſh Church,</hi> and <hi>Abrahams fleſhly Seed;</hi> ſo they ſhould <hi>take it for granted, that God would make it good, for God had Sworn it;</hi> and as they were a <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> and in <hi>Goſpel Order,</hi> and the <hi>Seed of Abraham <hi>by Faith,</hi>
                  </hi> ſo they ſhould <hi>take it for granted,</hi> and <hi>without diſpute,</hi> that <hi>whatſoever bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit God had <hi>Sworn</hi> to perform to the <hi>Seed of Faith,</hi> by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> our high Prieſt whom he hath <hi>Sworn <hi>is</hi>
                  </hi> a Prieſt <hi>for ever, after the Order of Melchiſedec:</hi> And being thus laid down as aforeſaid; not that they ſhould Swear as <hi>men,</hi> or <hi>the World Sware,</hi> but to make uſe of what the Lord Sware to, as men make uſe of their Swearing, to put out of doubt, that which is Sworn to, to be a real abſolute and final concluſion, and that which in due time, without dout will be by him made good; and if laid down for this end, and not as a Rule, Pattern or Preſident for them to act by, why then is this Scripture made uſe of, and ſo often brought to the Eyes and Ears of Goſpel Diſciples, to prove the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Swearing, contrary to the requirements of the Lord Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, who ſay, <hi>Swear not,</hi> and <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> and that by thy ſelf <hi>Henry Den</hi> page 4. <hi>John Tombs,</hi> in his Book, and <hi>Jeremiah Ives,</hi> page 11. and <hi>John Sturion</hi> and others by diſcourſes, who are <hi>Teachers</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:169357:9"/> of <hi>Congregations,</hi> and <hi>Leaders of People,</hi> and ſuch as for Humane parts, and eſpecially for <hi>Syllogiſtical Diſcourſes</hi> are eminent, and all or moſt of them in Print upon that account: And if either of you judge I have wronged you in what I have here ſaid, or the mind of the Spirit in the Text, <hi>Your mouths are open, and the Preſſe is free.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time, I ſhall in Chriſtian Love earneſtly beg you, and either of you, that you do not ſo comply with <hi>preſent ſelf Intereſts,</hi> as that you <hi>bank</hi> your <hi>own Conſciences,</hi> nor <hi>willingly extinguiſh that Light you have received,</hi> nor publiſh that in <hi>Print,</hi> nor <hi>privately diſcourſe</hi> that which may be inſtrumental to <hi>draw Souls</hi> from their <hi>Integrity,</hi> by <hi>poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning</hi> them with a <hi>carnal Indifferency in the things of God,</hi> either by your precept or example, as ſome of you have hitherto done, with the help of your Apoſtatized brother, <hi>Samuel Oats,</hi> to the hindring of mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes from entring into the Church of Chriſt, by your ſo violently op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that Principle of <hi>Laying on of Hands:</hi> But more of that in its due place, the which, that I may come to <hi>Henry Den,</hi> I ſhall ſay ſomething to thy pleading for the lawfulneſſe of Oaths amongſt Believers, upon the account of the frequentneſſe of Swearing amongſt Infidels; by which Carnal Reaſons and Arguing, thou mayeſt as well plead for the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Jews Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Popery,</hi> as do the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> from the <hi>Univerſality</hi> of their <hi>Church,</hi> to be the <hi>True Church,</hi> as with my ſelf ſeveral have done.</p>
               <p>In page the fifth, thou urgeſt the <hi>uſe</hi> of an <hi>Oath,</hi> in all <hi>Nations whatſoever,</hi> whether <hi>Jews, Gentiles,</hi> or <hi>Barbarians, between Prince and Subjects, Enemies and Friends,</hi> for the <hi>reconciling differences, ending of Controverſies, and aſſureance of Faith one towards the other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now (ſayeſt thou) <hi>How great is this Authority?</hi> namely, <hi>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all Nations;</hi> It is <hi>doubtleſſe,</hi> a <hi>demonſtration</hi> of the <hi>ſecond Rate</hi> at leaſt; ſome there are thou telleſt us, who account it of the firſt Rate, viz. <hi>That the Confent of Nations, is to be of Divine Authority; the which,</hi> however ſome may ſo aſſert, yet for <hi>thee,</hi> who <hi>pretendeſt</hi> thy ſelf to be what thou doeſt, and to ſay, <hi>doubtleſſe it is of Divine Authority,</hi> and of the <hi>ſecond Rate</hi> at <hi>the least,</hi> to me it ſeems no better than <hi>Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</hi> And that will be evident, when we <hi>conſider ſeriouſly</hi> the ſad <hi>conſequences</hi> of it; for <hi>Nations generally conſent to <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry,</hi>
                  </hi> as is evident; and this thoſe of the <hi>Papal Faction</hi> have <hi>urged</hi> to my ſelf in ſeveral <hi>Diſcourſes;</hi> to wit, that their <hi>way of Worſhip</hi> is the Truth, <hi>becauſe owned generally by all Nations.</hi> Now if this <hi>general conſent of all Nations,</hi> is to be to the Diſciples of Chriſt, of <hi>Divine Authority;</hi> Then I querie, firſt, Whether <hi>this be not to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169357:9"/> croſs and make void the ſayings of the Lord Chriſt,</hi> Luke 12.32. Who ſaith, <hi>Fear not <hi>little Flock,</hi> for it is your Fathers good pleaſure to give you the Kingdom;</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 15.19. <hi>I have choſen you out of the world, therefore the world ſhall hate you;</hi> And <hi>many are called, but few are choſen,</hi> Mat. 20.16. And <hi>ſtrait is the Gate, and narrow is the Way that leads to Life, and few</hi> there be <hi>that find it;</hi> becauſe, <hi>wide is the Gate, and broad is the way that leadeth to Deſtruction, and many there be that go in thereat,</hi> Mat. 7.13.</p>
               <p>And therefore, Secondly, I querie, <hi>Whether it be not of ſad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, to take the conſent of Nations for Divine Authority,</hi> which ſay, that <hi>generally</hi> all <hi>the Nations</hi> that are in that part of the world <hi>called Chriſtendom, <hi>are Chriſtians,</hi> and that they are all Believers;</hi> when Chriſt ſaith, <hi>that Chriſtians and Believers are a <hi>little Flock,</hi>
                  </hi> and that <hi>when the Son of Man cometh, he queſtions whether he ſhall find Faith on the earth,</hi> Luke 18.8. and are ſuch as do generally condemn the Generation of the Juſt?</p>
               <p>The next thing thou comeſt to, in page five, is to prove the <hi>lawfulneſs of Oaths in Goſpel Diſciples;</hi> ſaying, <hi>What doth it prove leſs, then that the taking of Oaths is one of the Dictates written and engraven in the Heart of man, by Natures Finger?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, That when perſons are wrought upon by <hi>true ſaving, juſtifying Faith,</hi> then it <hi>turns out Nature:</hi> I would not here be <hi>mistaken,</hi> I do not ſay, that <hi>Grace</hi> doth make a man <hi>unnatural,</hi> for that is a <hi>diſtinguiſhing character of a <hi>Reprobate condition</hi>
                  </hi> who are <hi>without underſtanding, Covenant breakers, without <hi>Natural affection,</hi> impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable-unmerciful,</hi> Rom. 1.31. So alſo ſaith our Apoſtle, ſuch are <hi>without <hi>Natural affection,</hi> Truce-breakers, falſe accuſers, incontinent, fierce, deſpiſers of thoſe that are good,</hi> 2 Pet. 3.3. but where True Grace comes, it works up Souls to a <hi>quickening,</hi> who were <hi>dead in treſpaſſes and ſins, among whom alſo they had their converſion in times paſt, fulfilling the deſires of the fleſh, and of the mind, and were by Nature the children of Wrath, as well as others; ſuch are raiſed up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and are made to ſit together in Heavenly Places, in Christ Jeſus,</hi> Epheſ. 2 1, 2. By all which we ſee, that what <hi>Nature Teacheth,</hi> is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally deſtroyed by Grace; that is, ſuch things as are unnatural, ſuch things as are contrary to the Mind of God, ſuch things as are con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rary to his Requirements, his word of Truth, ſuch things in which men know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by Pure Nature, they corrupt themſelves, <hi>Jude</hi> 10. And for thee to aſſert the <hi>dictates of Nature,</hi> to <hi>teach Goſpel Diſciples to Swear,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Nature teacheth them to Swear;</hi> to me it ſeems <hi>prepoſterous,</hi> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169357:10"/> that which is inconſiſtent with the word of Truth: For what <hi>Nation</hi> is there, <hi>Conſidered</hi> as a <hi>Nation,</hi> that at this day acteth according to <hi>pure Light of Nature?</hi> Nay, what <hi>particular Perſons</hi> are there, that act near it, but <hi>ſome few</hi> of that <hi>People called</hi> QUAKERS <hi>only?</hi> I ſhall Appeal to the Judgements of all herein, and ſhall juſtifie <hi>that People</hi> for <hi>that,</hi> and that <hi>above thoſe</hi> that do pretend to a <hi>Form of Godlineſs,</hi> and do <hi>deny the POWER thereof;</hi> for <hi>they acting onely and alone by the LIGHT within,</hi> and not Conforming at all to that which the Lord Chriſt hath left in the Holy Scriptures of Truth to be ſubjected to; and to which the Churches in the Primitive times have yielded their obedience; and yet they in moſt things, as to common actions between man and man, are <hi>ſome of them</hi> found acting juſtly and uprightly, and far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſome of thoſe that are in Goſpel-Order; and ſuch that at the <hi>Judgement Day</hi> will riſe up in Judgement againſt them, although they themſelves expect not to appear there; for they do not believe <hi>that Reſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for thee to <hi>poyſon</hi> a <hi>People</hi> with ſuch a <hi>palpable groſſe Errour,</hi> is an <hi>Evil</hi> of a <hi>Tranſcendant Nature;</hi> and to bend thy Abilities of Humane Learning, as ſome others have and do, to <hi>thwart</hi> the <hi>Dictates</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> and the <hi>Requirements</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> in <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. and <hi>James</hi> 5. is a matter of no ſmall dangerous Conſequence: For ſaith our <hi>Saviour, Whoſoever</hi> ſhall break one of theſe <hi>leaſt Commandements,</hi> and <hi>teach men ſo,</hi> ſhall be called <hi>leaſt</hi> in the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Matth. 5.19. And therefore I ſhall deſire thee to Query ſeriouſly with thine own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, whether thou comeſt not under that <hi>Wo</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.13. <hi>pronounced <hi>againſt thoſe who will not only refuſe to</hi> go in themſelves, <hi>nor yet ſuffer</hi> others to enter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next thing thou telleſt us of to perſwade us to Swear, is, that there is <hi>no Nation</hi> ſo <hi>Barbarous,</hi> but doth <hi>acknowledge</hi> the Religious uſe of an <hi>Oath,</hi> in calling their God <hi>to Witneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I <hi>Anſwer;</hi> If the <hi>Heathen</hi> and <hi>barbarous People,</hi> which have no <hi>knowledge</hi> of the <hi>true God,</hi> do <hi>Swear</hi> BY their <hi>falſe gods;</hi> doth it therefore follow that we, <hi>who have the knowledge of the TRUE GOD, and are in Gods own way and Worſhip, that we muſt TAKE EXAMPLE by them to SWEAR BY OUR GOD?</hi> And becauſe they, <hi>calling their god</hi> to <hi>witneſſe</hi> to what they <hi>do,</hi> they look upon <hi>that calling to witneſs</hi> to be <hi>SWEARING;</hi> muſt we needs be ſo <hi>ſenſleſs</hi> as to ſay, that <hi>calling our God to witneſs</hi> to the <hi>truth of what we ſay or do,</hi> that this is <hi>Swearing BY our God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next thing that I ſhall take notice of in <hi>Page</hi> 5. is, where thou uſeſt this Expreſſion; <hi>Now how can that thing be accompted Evil, which is approved by all Nations?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:169357:10"/>
               <p>To which I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> How canſt thou, O <hi>Henry Den,</hi> without <hi>bluſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> and <hi>calling thy Reaſon to queſtion,</hi> Query ſuch a thing? And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in thy next <hi>words,</hi> I muſt deſire thee to recollect thy <hi>Thoughts,</hi> and conſider what thou haſt <hi>ſaid</hi> in <hi>Print,</hi> and <hi>expoſed it to publick view.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou doſt deſire, <hi>That we would Recollect our Thoughts, and Conſider whether we can give one Inſtance of any one Evil, which hath been allowed and Approved by all Nations?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> The Worſhipping of <hi>falſe gods,</hi> or the <hi>true God <hi>after a falſe manner,</hi>
                  </hi> is the general courſe of <hi>all Nations;</hi> Now the Worſhipping of a <hi>falſe god,</hi> or of the <hi>true God</hi> after a <hi>falſe <hi>MANNER,</hi>
                  </hi> is an <hi>Evil,</hi> and a <hi>great one:</hi> And we know, that it is the <hi>Conſent</hi> of all <hi>Nations, to continue in a falſe way,</hi> and that in <hi>hatred</hi> and <hi>oppoſition</hi> to the <hi>true Worſhip and Service of God;</hi> the truth of which, I ſhall leave to the Godly Party to judge of.</p>
               <p>And in <hi>Page</hi> 6. thou Querieſt, <hi>Why we ſhould think it Unlawful to Swear, when the Conſent of Nations, the Example of Prophets, and Kings, and Righteous men of old; and in a condinued</hi> ſeries, <hi>for the moſt part, until this time; when the Example of Angels, yea, of Almighty God himſelf ſtands all at your Right hand: What one Practice is there that you have more, and greater Evidence for?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That all that hath been ſaid is to no <hi>purpoſe at all;</hi> for <hi>Conſent of Nations,</hi> can be <hi>no Rule</hi> for Goſpel Diſciples to <hi>walk by,</hi> becauſe they are required to walk by that <hi>Rule, Line,</hi> and <hi>Meaſure,</hi> that the Apoſtle walked by and acted in, who hath written and left the ſame to us for a <hi>Rule,</hi> and from which he and they did not dare to derogate, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.12. to 17. for our <hi>only <hi>care ought to be,</hi>
                  </hi> that <hi>our <hi>Converſation</hi>
                  </hi> be regulated <hi>according to the Goſpel,</hi> Phil. 1.27. and not by the Light within only, as ſome would have it; nor af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>manner</hi> of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> as thou wouldeſt have it, the which thou endeavoureſt to <hi>perſwade Souls</hi> to <hi>walk by:</hi> And therefore <hi>Query</hi> with thy ſelf, <hi>Henry Den,</hi> whether thou art not ſuch an one, who with <hi>cunning Craftineſs lieſt in wait to deceive,</hi> Eph. 4.14. and ſuch an one <hi>that goeth about to pervert the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 1.7. And if a <hi>Wo,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>ſaying</hi> of Chriſt, ſhall betide the <hi>Servants of Chriſt, when all men ſhall ſpeak well of them,</hi> Luk. 6.26. <hi>Query</hi> further with thy ſelf, <hi>Henry Den,</hi> how far thou art from that <hi>Wo,</hi> pronounced <hi>againſt</hi> thoſe that are <hi>blind Guides,</hi> who ſay, <hi>men may Swear, &amp;c.</hi> Mat. 23.16. and ſo endeavoureſt to <hi>perſwade</hi> them to <hi>Comply</hi> with all men in their Iniquities? And if the Apoſtle <hi>John's</hi> words be true, who ſaith, <hi>That the <hi>whole World</hi> lieth in <hi>wickedneſs,</hi>
                  </hi> 1 Joh. 5.19. and yet thou <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeſt</hi> us to walk by their Rule, <hi>directing us to it as Good,</hi> when the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169357:11"/> Spirit ſaith it is <hi>Evil;</hi> Whether doſt thou not pull down that Wo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thine own head, that is pronounced by the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Wo unto them that call <hi>good evil,</hi> and <hi>evil good;</hi> that put Light for Darkneſſe, and Darkneſſe for Light; that put Bitter for Sweet, and Sweet for Bitter?</hi> And whether thy deep humane Learning hath not puffed thee up, ſo as to ſeem wiſe in thine own eyes, and ſo thou plunge thy ſelf into <hi>Wo</hi> after <hi>Wo?</hi> for, <hi>Wo to them that are wiſe in their own eyes, and prudent in their own conceit,</hi> Iſa. 5.21.</p>
               <p>And further, If the <hi>Conſent and Practice of Nations</hi> be ſuch a direct Rule to walk by, as that it is of Divine Authority, as thou endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voureſt to beat us into a belief of it is; <hi>Why then art thou found under the Baptiſm of Believers; the which all Nations, conſidered as Nations, ſo much abominate, and walk contrary to?</hi> And whether thy words in print, and thy practice, do not evidently contradict each other? for by thy own Aſſertions thou ſhouldeſt be an Idolater, and a follower and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper of falſe gods.</p>
               <p>Therefore before I go further, I would deſire thee rationally to <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider</hi> and <hi>judge,</hi> whether thou ſpeakeſt by that Spirit, that <hi>leadeth into all Truth?</hi> or whether thou ſpeakeſt not out of a principle of <hi>Humane Learning,</hi> and as one of the Diſputers of this World, as the Wiſe, and as the Scribes, which God hath made <hi>fooliſhneſs,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. and ſo art become ſuch an one as our Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7. who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt to be a Teacher of ſuch a Law, as the Example and Conſent of Nations, is to be of Divine Authority, and ſo to learn the People of God to ſwear contrary to the Law of Chriſt; Whether art not thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſuch an one that knoweſt not what thou ſayeſt, nor whereof thou doeſt affirm, by thy thus endeavouring to perſwade to a diſobedience <hi>to Chriſt our Righteouſneſs, who is made of God unto us Wiſdom; whereby we ſpeak Righteouſneſs, by whom only we are accepted; <hi>Sanctification,</hi>
                  </hi> by and thorow whom we are <hi>choſen, ſeparated,</hi> and <hi>ſet apart;</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption,</hi> whoſe <hi>Blood ſpeaketh better things than that of <hi>Abel,</hi>
                  </hi> and by which <hi>only</hi> we are <hi>redeemed?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to proceed: Whereas thou telleſt us in pag. 6. <hi>That we have, together with the Conſent of Nations, and the Example of Prophets and Righteous men of old;</hi> ſo alſo <hi>the Authority of Angels, and God himſelf ſtanding at our right hand, as a <hi>warrant for Goſpel-Diſciples to ſwear.</hi>
                  </hi> To which I anſwer, Though we are required to <hi>follow God, as dear Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> and <hi>to walk in love,</hi> Eph. 5.1. <hi>To be holy,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.16. and <hi>to be perfect,</hi> Matth. 5.48. Yet we are no where required to follow him in ſwearing; neither is it a ſufficient Warrant for Goſpel-Diſciples to ſwear, <hi>becauſe God ſwore;</hi> and if we immitate him, we muſt immitate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169357:11"/> him in the <hi>manner</hi> and the <hi>end</hi> of his <hi>ſwearing:</hi> Now when the Lord ſwore, he <hi>ſwore by Himſelf;</hi> and for me to ſwear by my ſelf, is to break a Law of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.34. <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.12. which ſaith, <hi>Neither by thy Head,</hi> nor <hi>this,</hi> nor <hi>that,</hi> nor <hi>by any other Oath.</hi> Neither can I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him in his <hi>end,</hi> for I am not in ſuch a capacity as he was, or is in; And if I ſwear by him, I ſhall break a Law of Chriſt, who ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi> And if we can neither follow our Pattern in the <hi>manner,</hi> nor the <hi>end,</hi> for my own part, my ſhallow capacity is too narrow to apprehend why I ſhould in ſuch a caſe look upon ſuch a Leader: For to ſet a School-Boy a fair choice Copie, yet if he muſt not follow his Maſter, neither in a choice neat cutting his Letter, evenly and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly, keeping his line and diſtances, points and ſtops, how can he attain to fair writing, and to what end is his Copie laid before him?</p>
               <p>And as for <hi>Angels,</hi> the ſons &amp; daughters of men were never, as I know of, required to follow or immitate them; neither if they were, yet that ſwearing in <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.5, 6. cannot poſſibly be immitated, which is that <hi>one</hi> and <hi>only time,</hi> that ever we hear of <hi>Angels ſwearing;</hi> which was but <hi>One Angel,</hi> and but <hi>Once Swearing;</hi> and yet in pag. 6. thou telleſt us <hi>moſt deceitfully,</hi> that we have the <hi>Example of Angels,</hi> as if it were a <hi>common courſe for Angels to ſwear:</hi> By which the World ſhall ſee that the Spirit of the Lord ſpake a glorious truth in his ſervant <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 12.19. ſaying, <hi>The Lip of Truth ſhall be eſtabliſhed, but a <hi>Lying lip</hi> is but for a moment.</hi> For the <hi>Angels</hi> thou ſpeakeſt of, is but <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>Oath</hi> but <hi>one;</hi> and that one Oath <hi>neither before,</hi> nor <hi>under a Gospel Dispenſation;</hi> and therefore no Example for <hi>Gospel-Diſciples</hi> to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low: for the diſcovery of this <hi>one Angel's ſwearing,</hi> is by <hi>John the Revelator,</hi> who ſaw things to come; And he that ſhall aſſert, that that Angel did, or hath yet ſworn, may as ſafely and as truly ſay, <hi>The great Whore, that Mother of Harlots and all Abominations,</hi> is already brought down (though we ſee her ſetting up daily:) for this Angel ſhall not ſwear till ſhe be down; for when he ſhall ſwear, the end of his ſwearing, ſhall be to let us know, <hi>that time ſhall be no more,</hi> Revel. 10.6. and this thou urgeſt, as a <hi>Preſident</hi> for Goſpel-Diſciples to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; in doing which thou bringeſt it to as little purpoſe, as <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> and thy ſelf both, bring and urge that Text of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.16. thou in pag. 4. and he in pag. 9. though <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> be as palpably groſſe as thy ſelf therein; for in pag. 7. he giveth it in as a third reaſon why thoſe two Texts, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. and <hi>James</hi> 5. doth not forbid the uſe of all <hi>ſwearing,</hi> as was commanded under the Law; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, ſaith he, the <hi>Prophets,</hi> when he can bring but <hi>one Prophet</hi> for <hi>his Prophets;</hi> no more than thou <hi>Henry Den,</hi> canſt bring <hi>Angels</hi> for
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169357:12"/> that <hi>One Angel,</hi> as aforeſaid; and <hi>Propheſies,</hi> as thou ſayeſt in <hi>pag.</hi> 4. <hi>lin.</hi> 21. when it is but this <hi>one Propheſie,</hi> by that <hi>one Prophet</hi> thy Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> produced, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.16. So that here I muſt ſay to him, as before I ſaid to thee, from <hi>Prov.</hi> 12.19. <hi>That a lying tongue is but for a moment: Angels</hi> and <hi>Prophets;</hi> as if there were multitudes, when there is but <hi>one Angel,</hi> and <hi>one Prophet</hi> produced, and that <hi>Angel</hi> and that <hi>Prophet,</hi> making but two in all, (and leſſe there cannot be to make the plural number) yet both cannot produce one good <hi>Warrant</hi> for what they are brought; for the end why this ſuppoſed multitude of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> are brought for, is, but to perſwade <hi>Gospel-Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> to break that Law of Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. and <hi>James</hi> 5. and when all is done, when from this ſuppoſed Mountain of <hi>Swearing</hi> ſomething remarkable is expected to be brought forth, (to ſpeak metaphorically) it amounteth not to ſo much as a Mouſe; for a Mouſe is ſomething in being, but this is nothing at all as to <hi>Gospel-Diſciples,</hi> for it concerns not their Diſpenſation in the leaſt; for, as to the <hi>Angel's ſwearing,</hi> as is aforeſaid, it is <hi>not yet acted;</hi> and when it ſhall be acted, it ſhall ſet a <hi>period to time,</hi> and it ſhall not be <hi>till time ſhall be no more,</hi> as to men upon Earth.</p>
               <p>So ſecondly, When that Swearing ſhall be which is ſpoken of by that <hi>one Teſtimony,</hi> that <hi>one Prophet,</hi> called <hi>Prophets,</hi> that alſo ſhall be fulfilled in ſuch a juncture of time, when the <hi>Gospel-Lamps</hi> of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion ſhall be out,</hi> for it ſhall be then when there ſhall be a <hi>New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and a <hi>New Earth,</hi> as ſaith <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> himſelf from that 56th Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ver. 17. <hi>It ſhall be, that when the New Heavens and the New Earth are created, and when the former Heavens and the former Earth is forgotten:</hi> So that if it ſhall be <hi>then,</hi> and not till then, that the former Earth and Heaven ſhall be forgotten, that this ſwearing ſhall be that is here ſpoken of; when they that ſwear, ſhall <hi>ſwear by the God of Truth;</hi> And if ſo, then it is not in truth to be <hi>bound upon Gospel-Diſciples:</hi> And that ye may know diſtinctly <hi>When</hi> it ſhall be, and <hi>Whom</hi> they ſhall be that ſhall ſwear: as to the time <hi>when,</hi> the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> will tell us, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.7. that by the <hi>ſame Power that made the Heavens and the Earth, they are kept in ſtore, reſerved unto fire, <hi>againſt the day of Iudgment, and perdition of ungodly men.</hi>
                  </hi> And this is that which maketh ſome of us <hi>patiently wait for,</hi> and yet <hi>haſte unto the coming of the <hi>Day of God,</hi> wherein the Heavens being on fire, ſhall be diſſolved, and the Earth ſhall melt with fervent heat;</hi> then it is when we, <hi>according to his Promiſe, look for a <hi>New Heaven</hi> and a <hi>New Earth,</hi> wherein dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth RIGHTEOUSNESS,</hi> or CHRIST, <hi>who of God is made unto us, Wiſdom, RIGHTEOUSNESS,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 1.30. <hi>Who
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169357:12"/> is the Lord our RIGHTEOUSNESSE,</hi> Jerem. 23.6.</p>
               <p>And as to the perſons who they ſhall be, the 15th verſe of the 65th Chapter tells us, That they are ſuch as ſhall be called by another name; And this Evangelical Prophet diſtinguiſheth them from the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> whom we are; for ſo ſaith he, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.2. ſpeaking of <hi>them, <hi>And the Gentiles ſhall ſee</hi> Thy Righteouſneſs, <hi>and all Kings</hi> thy Glory; <hi>Thou ſhalt alſo be a</hi> Crown of Glory <hi>in the Hand of the Lord, and a Royal Diadem in the Hand of thy God. Thou ſhalt no more be termed, FORSAKEN, neither ſhall Thy LAND any more be termed DESOLATE; For</hi> Thou <hi>ſhalt be called HEPHZI-BAH, and Thy Land BEULAH: for the Lord delighteth in Thee, and thy Land ſhall be Married: For as a young man marrieth a Virgin, ſo ſhall thy ſons marry thee;</hi>
                  </hi> (ſpeaking to the <hi>Land</hi> or <hi>Beulah) <hi>And as a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom rejoyceth over his Bride, ſo ſhall thy God rejoyce over thee.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this the Lord hath ſworn to <hi>by his Right hand,</hi> and <hi>by the Arm of his Strength,</hi> that <hi>he will perform it.</hi> And this ſhall be, when he will no more give their Corn nor their Wine, for which they have laboured, into the hands of their Enemies nor Strangers, when they ſhall call them, <hi>The Holy People, The Redeemed of the Lord: <hi>and their Land ſhall be called</hi> Sought out, a City not forſaken.</hi> So that it ſhall be <hi>ſcattered Iſrael</hi> that ſhall thus ſwear, when his Name ſhall be changed, and no more called <hi>Forſaken</hi> or <hi>caſt out;</hi> but when he ſhall be called <hi>Hephzi-bah,</hi> and that after a Goſpel-diſpenſation, when the <hi>former Heavens</hi> and the <hi>former Earth</hi> ſhall be <hi>forgotten;</hi> then alſo ſhall <hi>your Angel ſwear.</hi> So that thine and thy Brother <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> great noiſe of <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> being but <hi>two in all,</hi> and <hi>one</hi> of them named <hi>as if he had ſworn a great while ſince,</hi> when in truth <hi>they ſhall neither of them ſwear,</hi> till the <hi>Hand</hi> of the Lord ſhall be <hi>known</hi> towards his <hi>Servants,</hi> and his <hi>Indignation</hi> towards his <hi>Enemies: For, behold! the Lord will come with Fire, and with his Chariots like a Whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind, to render his Anger with <hi>Fury,</hi> and his Rebuke with <hi>Flames of Fire:</hi> for by Fire and by Sword, ſhall the Lord plead with all fleſh; and the ſlain of the Lord ſhall be many,</hi> Iſa. 66.15, 16.</p>
               <p>And now conſider, you great <hi>Humane Learned men,</hi> to what end was this noiſe of <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Prophets</hi> thus proclaimed, <hi>to ſtand at our right hand, to perſwade us to ſwear,</hi> when, upon examination, they <hi>know not what they had to do there;</hi> the which if it be thought they have, I ſhall leave to the Rational to judge of, whilſt I take thoſe other Prophets and Righteous men of old that ſtand with them, into queſtion alſo, to hear whether they can perſwade us to ſwear.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:169357:13"/>
               <p>And upon examination, I find that which they have to ſay to us, is, that they under that Legal Adminiſtration given out by the hand of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> had, <hi>Thus ſaith the Word of the Lord for their <hi>Warrant,</hi>
                  </hi> Deut. 8.13. <hi>Thou ſhalt Fear the Lord thy God, and ſhalt Swear by his Name:</hi> And now I muſt apply my ſelf to <hi>Henry Den</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah Ives,</hi> and let them know, that theſe <hi>Prophets and Holy men of old,</hi> were under the <hi>Levitical Priesthood;</hi> but <hi>now the Prieſthood is changed,</hi> and as the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> is <hi>changed,</hi> ſo there <hi>muſt needs be alſo a change of the Law,</hi> Heb. 7.12. So <hi>They</hi> were <hi>under Moſes the Servant,</hi> but <hi>We</hi> are under the <hi>Son, <hi>who was counted worthy of more Honour than</hi>
                  </hi> Moſes, <hi>in as much as he who hath builded the houſe,</hi> hath <hi>more honour than the houſe; and though</hi> Moſes <hi>was faithful in his houſe as a Servant, yet Chriſt as a Son</hi> over his <hi>OWN HO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SE;</hi> whoſe houſe are we, Heb. 3, 3, 5. <hi>And if the SON make us free, then are we free in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,</hi> John 8.36. <hi>Therefore hear what the Son faith, It hath been ſaid to them</hi> of old time, that were under my <hi>Servant Moſes, Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>But I ſay unto you, I that am a Son over mine own Houſe, I who will make you free from Swearing;</hi> and <hi>ſo,</hi> or by that means, free from <hi>Forſwearing;</hi> I ſay unto you, <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> So that we being under the Sons Prieſthood, we are freed from all things that were under the Servants Law, and that by the <hi>Direction</hi> of that <hi>Spirit</hi> that was ſent to lead into all Truth, and to ſhew things to come, and that from <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28. and <hi>Acts</hi> 21.26. <hi>For as touching the Gentiles which believe,</hi> we have <hi>written</hi> and <hi>concluded, that they obſerve no ſuch things, SAVE ONELY that they keep THEM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SELVES</hi> from <hi>IDOLS,</hi> and from <hi>BLOOD,</hi> and from things <hi>STRANGLED,</hi> and from <hi>FORNICATION;</hi> And ſeeing it is ſo, that thou and thy brother <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> do ſo oppoſe our Maſter and his <hi>Houſhold,</hi> I ſhall in the <hi>Power, ſtreng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h</hi> and <hi>might</hi> of my Maſter, examine your grounds as a faithful Sentinel, before you farther paſſe our Guard; leſt if ye get within us, and by flattery, <hi>Dalilah</hi>-like, you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reave us of our ſtrength.</p>
               <p>In page 7. <hi>Jerem. Ives</hi> tells of <hi>Voluntary Oaths,</hi> the which I ſay with him, were lawful, under that diſpenſation; but he bringeth nothing at all to prove them to be ſo now under a Goſpel-diſpenſation, but his own <hi>ſay-ſo,</hi> onely; ſo that <hi>all that</hi> he hath done in all the ſix pages before, was <hi>but onely to fill up his two ſheets, and nothing at all to the purpoſe:</hi> for our Lord Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. <hi>It hath been ſaid to them of old time, Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, but I ſay unto you Swear not at all;</hi> So that he needed not have gone ſo far about the wood, to have proved
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169357:13"/> that <hi>which was never denyed.</hi> And had he but cut off ſomething ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous behind, and this before, one pair of ſheets might have ſerved both his and his brother <hi>Henry Dens</hi> Reaſons, to have lain in againſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. and <hi>James</hi> 5.12. And therefore I ſhall give a brief account of what he ſaith in oppoſition to <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> To which in page 7. he doth anſwer negatively, that that Text cannot forbid the uſe of all Swearing, that was lawful under the Law; his firſt Reaſon is, Becauſe Chriſt himſelf <hi>Swore, Mat.</hi> 26.63. when the Prieſt ſaid, <hi>I Adjure thee by the Living God, that thou tell me whether thou be the Chriſt, the Son of God.</hi> And ſaith <hi>Jeremiah Ives, Chriſt Sware</hi> in his ſaying, <hi>thou haſt ſaid,</hi> or, <hi>I am.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I <hi>Anſwer,</hi> That he did not Swear, and that by <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> his own ſhewing; for in p. 11. l. 1. <hi>We ſhall prove that it was the Priest <hi>Sware,</hi> and not Christ:</hi> for if <hi>the Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>did Swear when he Adjured,</hi> 1 Theſ. 5.27. <hi>and not them he writ to;</hi> then the Prieſt Sware (if Adjuring be Swearing) and not Chriſt when he was Adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but ſaith <hi>Jeremiah Ives, The Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>Sware when he Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured,</hi> and this he juſtifies in p. 11. l. 1. &amp; in l. 17. he thinketh it no preſumption to arraign them for Ignorance, that ſay, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul did evil in Swearing;</hi> the which I will not ſay, for I really judge as I have ſhewed in p. 11, 12. that Adjuring is not Swearing; yet by the way, I would have <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> know, <hi>That it would be well for him if he could clear himſelf of groſſe Ignorance,</hi> in aſſerting what he hath aſſerted.</p>
               <p>Saith he, <hi>The Apoſtle Swore when he Adjured by the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>he Adjured the Brethren,</hi> for 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.27. <hi>I charge you by the Lord, that this Epiſtle be read to all the Holy Brethren, <hi>I charge you:</hi>
                  </hi> Who? <hi>You Brethren into whoſe hands it ſhall come;</hi> for compare this with 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1. and you ſhall find it was written to the Church, conſidered as a Church; and as I judge at this time without Officers, for we read of none they had; for being in the Infancy of the Church, I judge there were none yet found fitly qualified for the work, neither in that Church, nor in the <hi>Roman, Corinthian, Galatian</hi> nor <hi>Epheſian,</hi> nor the <hi>Coloſſian</hi> Churches; for had there been any, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle would, I judge, have written to them that were Officers, as well as to the Brethren, and in this as well as in other Churches to the Elders; For writing to the Church of <hi>Philippi,</hi> he writeth to all the Saints in Chriſt Jeſus which are at <hi>Philippi,</hi> with the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Deacons;</hi> and the Lord Chriſt ſending <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Revelator</hi> to the ſeven Churches in <hi>Aſia, Rev.</hi> 1.4.11. he directeth all his Matter to the Angels of thoſe Churches,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169357:14"/> 
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.8, 12, 18. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1, 7, 14. But that <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> might perſwade us to a belief in what he hath done in Swearing, is juſtifiable and lawful; and to perſwade others alſo thereunto, he hath moſt groſly Adulterated that Scripture cited for his purpoſe; for ſaith he, page 11. line the firſt and ſecond, <hi>To Adjure, is to exact an Oath,</hi> or to require the <hi>party Adjured</hi> to Swear; ſo that he would make us believe, that <hi>Paul</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured ſome other Apoſtle that he wrote to, to Swear; and therefore he, as I ſaid before, gives us a wrong ſenſe of the Scripture, for ſaith the Text. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.27. I <hi>charge <hi>you:</hi>
                  </hi> the Text ſaith not, I charge <hi>thee,</hi> but <hi>you</hi> as aforeſaid; and it is evident that the Text ſaith not, you <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> but you <hi>Church,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.1. for then would <hi>Jer. Ives</hi> in p 11. l. 15. when he ſaid, That thoſe that ſaid the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> did evil in <hi>Swearing,</hi> would have ſaid <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in the plural number; ſo that from <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> his own ſhewing, it was the <hi>Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>not <hi>Chriſt</hi> Sware,</hi> when he <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured,</hi> as well as it was the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> Paul <hi>Sware</hi> when he <hi>Adjured</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Theſſalonians; If an Adjuration be an Oath or Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> there is much after his Aſſertion in page 10. l. 28, 29. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where he doth cite <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.1. in which ſaith <hi>Jeremiah Ives, The Apoſtle Sware by Christ;</hi> for ſaith he a little before, in line 21. <hi>If calling God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to what I ſay, be not Swearing, I confeſſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I am igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant what Swearing is;</hi> and now this is <hi>Swearing by Chriſt, ſaith he,</hi> when he called not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but his <hi>Conſcience to Witneſſe;</hi> and by his own ſhewing, if the <hi>Thing or Party</hi> called to Witneſſe, be the <hi>Thing</hi> or <hi>Party Sworn by,</hi> then the Apoſtle <hi>Sware by his Conſcience,</hi> for ſo ſaith the Text, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.1. <hi>I ſpeak the Truth, in Christ I lie not, my <hi>Conſcience</hi> beareth me Witneſſe in the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> ſo that this is <hi>more then ever the Law allowed,</hi> which this Text is brought to prove; So that I may ſay to <hi>Jeremiah Ives,</hi> after the manner of the Speech of the Prophet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Eſau, Obadiah</hi> 6. <hi>How are the things of</hi> Jeremiah Ives <hi>ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out? <hi>how are his hidden things</hi> ſought out?</hi> And this I would have <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> know, that we are ſenſible of that according to his own ſaying, in page 11. line 18. <hi>that he that contrary to the Law of God, will <hi>Swear,</hi> will alſo <hi>Lie.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>But farther, I would earneſtly deſire that this be minded, that this Text, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.27. ſaith, I <hi>charge you,</hi> &amp;c. and this by <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> his own ſhewing, is equivolent with, <hi>I Adjure</hi> thee, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.63. So that to <hi>charge by,</hi> and in <hi>ones Name,</hi> and <hi>to Adjure</hi> by, or in <hi>ones Name, is all one, to which I willingly aſſent;</hi> yet this <hi>Charging,</hi> is no more <hi>Swearing by</hi> that <hi>Party,</hi> then is the ſaid <hi>Conſtables, Charging</hi> or <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring</hi> in the <hi>Name,</hi> or by the <hi>Power of the KING, Swearing by
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169357:14"/> the King,</hi> as in <hi>page</hi> 11. And if it be <hi>Swearing by the King,</hi> yet it is not the party ſubmitting to the ſaid Conſtables Command that ſwears <hi>by the King,</hi> but the <hi>Conſtable,</hi> who in the Kings Name doth ſo <hi>adjure</hi> or <hi>command,</hi> as <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> himſelf hath fully ſhewed, as ye ſee evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently: But I hope I have ſaid enough in <hi>pag.</hi> 11, 12. to prove <hi>Adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, No Swearing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But a ſecond thing I have by way of <hi>Exception</hi> againſt the firſt Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>That Chriſt ſware;</hi> And that is this, which I would willingly have well minded. <hi>Jeremiah Ives,</hi> both <hi>pag.</hi> 7. <hi>line</hi> 17 &amp; 18. telleth us, that it is in the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> and in <hi>pag.</hi> 11. <hi>line</hi> 9, 10. in <hi>Beza's Engliſh</hi> Bible, it is (ſaith he) <hi>He charged him to ſwear:</hi> So that in plain Engliſh, <hi>Christ did not ſwear,</hi> for his Anſwer was according to what his Command was to us, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.34. <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> but <hi>let your Yea, be Yea, and your Nay, Nay;</hi> and ſo was his: for without Swearing, he telleth him in ſo many words, as <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> ſaith, in <hi>pag.</hi> 7. <hi>line</hi> 21. <hi>Thou haſt ſaid,</hi> or, <hi>I am,</hi> which was <hi>no ſwearing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall now go on in the work a little further, nothing doubting but in the ſtrength of the Lord, and in the Power of his Might, in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion to overthrow all Oppoſitions to the Honour and Glory of my Maſter, King <hi>JESUS.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſecondly, ſaith he, <hi>This Text,</hi> Matth. 5.34. <hi>cannot take away all Swearing that was lawful under the Law, becauſe theſe Commandments contained in Ordinances were not taken away, <hi>till the death of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi>
                  </hi> Epheſ. 2.15. <hi>till he <hi>had nailed them to his Croſſe,</hi>
                  </hi> Coloſſians, 2.19.</p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, That the Lord Chriſt, on this ſide the Grave, (which was before a pure Goſpel-diſpenſation) was laying down <hi>Laws, Statutes</hi> and <hi>Appointments,</hi> that were to be obſerved <hi>beyond the Grave,</hi> I mean <hi>after his riſing out of the Grave,</hi> and <hi>under a pure Goſpel-diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation:</hi> for that is a pure Coſpel-diſpenſation, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. He was before his Death in this, as in other things, making way for his <hi>Univerſal Commiſſion,</hi> Matth. 28.20. <hi>Teaching them to obſerve all things, whatſoever I have commanded you:</hi> So that his Commands were laid down <hi>before his Death,</hi> on <hi>this ſide the Grave;</hi> as was <hi>Breaking of Bread in the Night he was Betrayed, Church-dealing, Matth.</hi> 18.15. And thus, in <hi>ſeveral caſes,</hi> he was ordering what ſhould be <hi>obſerved in his Houſe,</hi> when it ſhould <hi>become a Goſpel-Houſe;</hi> And this was no other but the <hi>Pattern in the Mount:</hi> As for inſtance, Suppoſe a Maſter of a Family is to go a great Journey, he telleth his Servants before-hand what he would have them to do in ſome caſes, and giveth his Servants a ſtrict charge alſo how they ſhould demean and behave themſelves in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169357:15"/> ſuch and ſuch buſineſſes; and telleth them further, that he will ſend to them further directions, and that by a <hi>ſure hand,</hi> what they ſhall fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do in order to the well-managing and ordering his Affairs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring their care therein; telling them withall, that his Journey is of weighty concernment, and that which will conduce both to his and their future well-being; and ſo we will ſuppoſe him gone.</p>
               <p>Juſt ſo it was with the Lord Chriſt, he gave out ſeveral Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as aforeſaid, promiſing that they ſhould hear from him with more Directions, for ſo faith he himſelf, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16.12. <hi>I have yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things to ſay unto you, howbeit you cannot bear them now; but when the <hi>Spirit of Truth</hi> is come, he ſhall guide you into all</hi> Truth; —<hi>And he ſhall ſhew you</hi> Things <hi>to come.</hi> And ſo he tells them, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.1, 2, <hi>&amp;c. Let not your Hearts be troubled; ye believe in God, believe alſo in me: in my Fathers Houſe are many Manſions; I go to prepare a place for you; And if I go to prepare a place for you, I will come to you again, and will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you to my ſelf, that where I am there ye may be alſo; And I tell you the truth, it is expedient for you that I go away; and if I go not away, the</hi> Comforter <hi>will not</hi> come <hi>unto you: But if I go away, I will</hi> ſend him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.7. And this we know that our Maſter, <hi>that certain Nobleman,</hi> Luk. 19.11. <hi>is gone into a far Countrey to receive for himſelf a Kingdom, and to return; and at his return thoſe his Servants that</hi> ſhook off his YOAK, <hi>that would not that his</hi> Bonds <hi>ſhould hold, thoſe that turn their</hi> Backs <hi>upon the</hi> MEETINGS <hi>of his PEOPLE,</hi> for fear of the <hi>Corporal Penalty</hi> of the breach of <hi>Proclamation, run and hide</hi> themſelves both from the <hi>Folds,</hi> and alſo from the <hi>Sheep of Chriſt;</hi> and thoſe Paſtors that fed not his Sheep, his Lambs, his tender Ones; and thoſe <hi>Sheep</hi> and <hi>Lambs</hi> that refuſed to come to the <hi>feeding-places,</hi> but either lay <hi>lazing</hi> and <hi>lurking</hi> at <hi>Home,</hi> or elſe were <hi>ſtragling</hi> up and down in <hi>Woods</hi> and <hi>Thickets,</hi> and amongſt <hi>Briary Brambles;</hi> and thoſe that <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el-like</hi> were ready to run back again to the <hi>Fleſh-pots,</hi> the <hi>Garlick,</hi> the <hi>Onyons,</hi> and the <hi>flaſhy, watery, infectious Cucumbers</hi> and <hi>Melons</hi> of <hi>Egypt;</hi> thoſe that are willing to <hi>ſave</hi> their <hi>Lives here,</hi> though they <hi>loſe them to Eternity:</hi> for when he cometh, he ſhall <hi>Separate</hi> the <hi>Sheep</hi> from the <hi>Goats;</hi> and he ſhall ſay to them <hi>on his Right hand, Come ye Bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdom prepared for you from the foundation of the World,</hi> Matth. 25.34. And then ſhall he bring that <hi>Wo</hi> pronounced againſt <hi>Careleſſe Shepherds,</hi> Ezek. 34.4. to which for brevities ſake, I ſhall deſire at your leiſures to refer you to make application according to this our <hi>Abominable Back-ſliding Times:</hi> and though I have been upon a Digreſſion, I hope it may be an Inſtrument in Gods hand to lead us the neareſt way home.</p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:169357:15"/>
               <p>Neither do I judge it altogether unſeaſonable to thee <hi>Henry Den,</hi> nor <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> and <hi>John Tombes,</hi> for I fear that he that will be ſo ready to break a Command of Chriſt to <hi>Swear for Self-Intereſt,</hi> will be as ready to <hi>turn his back upon the Sheep,</hi> as well as on the <hi>Shepherd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I muſt ſay to thee <hi>Jeremiah Ives,</hi> as thou thy ſelf ſayeſt, <hi>page</hi> 11. <hi>line</hi> 18. <hi>That he that will ſwear, will lye;</hi> the meaning of it, ſayeſt thou, is, That he that will <hi>ſwear wickedly,</hi> and <hi>contrary to Gods Law,</hi> will <hi>lye alſo.</hi> Examine thine own heart, and ſet a watch before the door of thy lips; and <hi>ſuffer not thy tongue to cauſe thy fleſh to ſin;</hi> but <hi>ſmite</hi> upon thy <hi>Thigh,</hi> and ſay, <hi>What have I done?</hi> how am I taken in mine own ſnare? how am I payed with mine own coyn?</p>
               <p>And becauſe of this ſeaſonable word, I ſhall reſolve to be briefer in what I have to ſay, as to <hi>Jeremiah Ives,</hi> being I have diſtinguiſhed between <hi>Vows, Oaths, &amp;c.</hi> having anſwered <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.15. which is the moſt material Text to give ſatisfaction; to the which, however, if ſo good an Anſwer could not have been given, as is aforeſaid, yet by <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> his own ſhewing, it is now made void ſince the death of the Teſtator: for, ſaith he in <hi>page</hi> 7. <hi>line</hi> 28. <hi>Theſe Commandments contained in Ordinances, were not taken away till the death of the Teſtator, Eph.</hi> 2.15. And, ſaith he, <hi>THESE ORDINANCES that were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to us, were not taken away, till Chriſt nailed them to his Croſſe,</hi> Col. 2.24. So that Chriſt nailed them to his Croſs above 1600. years agone; And ever ſince, by <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> his own ſhewing, they have been made void: for what he nailed to his Croſſe, <hi>is blotted out;</hi> ſo that all his great ado that he makes in his firſt ſix pages, and all that is multiplyed afterwards, is all to no purpoſe: therefore I may ſay to thee, as I ſaid to thy Brother <hi>Henry Den, That God taketh the Wiſe in their own craftineſs;</hi> and ſhall let thee know, that by <hi>plowing with Gods heifer,</hi> I have made a <hi>quick riddance of my work;</hi> and ſhall no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger fight with him, ſeeing I have the victory: for if (by his own ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) <hi>they are nailed to Chriſts Croſſe;</hi> it is evident, that all that in reaſon can be pleaded beyond this, cannot take upon us, unleſs he can find us an appointment for the raking it out of his Grave again.</p>
               <p>And now I ſhall in the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the Lord, and in the <hi>Power of his Might,</hi> cry out and ſay, <hi>Good is yet the Word of the Lord,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.34. <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now I ſhall come to thee <hi>Henry Den,</hi> for in <hi>page</hi> 6. thou alſo bringeſt in theſe two Texts, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. and <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. by way of objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, telling us that thou haſt an Exception againſt the <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the Greek renders the word, <hi>Not at all, <hi>wholly,</hi>
                  </hi> or <hi>altogether;</hi> ſo that in the proper ſpeech it ſhould be read, <hi>Swear not <hi>wholly,</hi>
                  </hi> or
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169357:16"/> 
                  <hi>altogether,</hi> let not your <hi>whole Communication</hi> be <hi>interwoven with Oaths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I anſwer, That the ſame ſenſe that thou bringeſt from the Greek <hi>may as well ſpeak the truth,</hi> as <hi>not at all;</hi> for to me it ſeems to be no more but this, As if the Lord Chriſt ſhould have ſaid, <hi>It hath been ſaid to them of old time, Thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf, &amp;c. but I ſay unto you, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi>
                  </hi> (but to prevent the danger of Forſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) I ſay unto you, <hi>Let your Communication be <hi>wholly</hi> and <hi>altogether</hi> without Oaths.</hi> And what doth your Greek Tranſlation <hi>wholly</hi> and <hi>alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> differ from the ſenſe of our Tranſlation? Doth it ſpeak any thing more or leſſe than what the Text ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> or, <hi>Let your Communication</hi> be <hi>wholly</hi> and <hi>altogether without Oaths?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Something there is that is forbidden by the Lord Chriſt, when he ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which if it ſhall be anſwered, that he <hi>only forbad Swearing in common communication,</hi> I ſhall to that ſay, <hi>That that kind of Swearing was never lawful;</hi> And in his forbidding that which was never lawful, he ſhall reiterate that which was alwayes unlawful, and had <hi>nothing at all to ſay to it;</hi> when he had <hi>nothing at all to ſay to it,</hi> when he had <hi>named it,</hi> ſeemeth to me to be an <hi>Impertinency;</hi> and to ſay that he ſpake <hi>Impertinencies,</hi> to me it ſeems altogether <hi>Impertinent.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here are two things ſpoken of, firſt, <hi>Forſwearing:</hi> Secondly, <hi>Swearing in Common Converſe</hi> or <hi>Communication;</hi> and both being unlawful, we muſt rationally conclude, that by the Lord Chriſt they are <hi>both forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den:</hi> and if ſo, then let us ſet our <hi>Reaſon</hi> on work, to conſider ſeriouſly how theſe two <hi>unlawful things</hi> are forbidden: he ſaith not, <hi>thou ſhalt not forſwear thy ſelf,</hi> as it was ſaid to them of old, <hi>to the one;</hi> and to the <hi>other,</hi> Swear <hi>not at all;</hi> if he had, then Swearing might have been law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>now</hi> as well as of old: for, a forbidding to <hi>Forſwear,</hi> implyes a <hi>lawfulneſs to ſwear;</hi> but if <hi>Swearing be not lawful,</hi> then there is no room for a <hi>forbidding to forſwear; Forſwearing</hi> is then out of doors, for no <hi>ſwearing,</hi> and therefore no poſſibility of <hi>forſwearing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I ſay, let us conſider of theſe two unlawful things, <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing</hi> and <hi>Swearing</hi> in <hi>Common Communication:</hi> And let us ſee how they are forbidden, and then I hope there will appear ſome light in the caſe, that by the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>Lords Light,</hi> thou <hi>Henry Den,</hi> and thy Brother <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> may ſee <hi>Light.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We uſually ſay in our common Proverb, <hi>It is good killing two birds with one ſtone:</hi> And the Lord Chriſt doth the ſame thing in effect in this place: for he forbids both theſe unlawful things (though diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent) in one breath, when he ſayes, <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid to both of them diſtinctly thus, <hi>Swear not at all, as to common
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169357:16"/> communication,</hi> becauſe never lawfull; And, <hi>Swear not at all</hi> in other things, leſt poſſibly you may in <hi>Swearing, forſwear</hi> your ſelves: But becauſe the difference in the Tranſlation is the main thing upon which thou wouldeſt turn the ſenſe of the letter of this Scripture upon, I ſhall once more, for a more perfect clearing up of the caſe, take thine own <hi>terms</hi> in thine own <hi>tranſlation,</hi> and read the ſentence according to them; and therein I hope there will appear ſo much <hi>contradiction of truth,</hi> as that thou wilt change thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nd, and be ready to ſay, <hi>it is in vain to kick againſt the pricks;</hi> it is an evil thing and a bitter to be found fighting againſt God, by endeavouring to <hi>pervert the way of truth,</hi> to the <hi>turning the blind and ignorant out of the way,</hi> to the <hi>bringing Gods Curſe upon thine own head,</hi> Deut. 27.18. Therefore in the fear of the Lord, and with mature deliberation and due conſideration, let us reade the ſentence in thine own words: <hi>Let your Communication be wholly and altogether without Swearing; Either by the true God, leſt ye take the Name of God in vain;</hi> or <hi>by any other Oath, leſt ye become Idolaters in ſetting up ſomething elſe to ſwear by, inſtead of the true God: Therefore, <hi>ſwear not at all,</hi> neither by this, that, or any other Oath; but let your Yea be Yea, and your Nay, Nay; for whatſoever is more than this, cometh of Evil, or from that Evil one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And to the other thus, according to thy Greek rendring: <hi>Forbear Swearing wholly, and altogether, leſt poſſibly in Swearing, ye Forſwear your ſelves: but let your Yea, be Yea, and your Nay, Nay; for what is more than this cometh of Evil, or of, or from that Evil one.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now let the Rational judge both of thy <hi>Tranſlation</hi> and thy <hi>Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and my <hi>Anſwer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place I ſhall lay before thee <hi>thine own words,</hi> and ſhall deſire thee to be <hi>thine own Judge, in what thou haſt gone contrary to Truth in;</hi> And ſeeing they are <hi>the things of God</hi> that we are upon, be perſwaded to lay aſide thy <hi>Humane Learning,</hi> and thy <hi>great Scholar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip:</hi> The which far be it from me to <hi>condemn,</hi> either as <hi>unlawful,</hi> or <hi>unprofitable in their places;</hi> yet in this caſe I would have them take no place at all, becauſe it is the work of another: yea, ſo ſaith our Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10, 11. <hi>For what man knoweth the things of a man, but the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of a man that is in him.</hi> Even ſo (or juſt in the ſame manner) <hi>the <hi>things of God</hi> knoweth no man, but the <hi>Spirit of God.</hi>
                  </hi> And if it be the <hi>Spirit of God only,</hi> then it is not <hi>Humane Learning:</hi> And if it be the <hi>Spirit</hi> only that <hi>ſearcheth all things,</hi> yea, <hi>the deep things of God,</hi> then it is not great <hi>Scholarſhip,</hi> nor ſtrength of parts that doth it.</p>
               <p>And if thou <hi>findeſt not</hi> ſuch a <hi>fulneſſe of the Spirit,</hi> as to ſearch out the depth of the <hi>deep things of God;</hi> then <hi>conſider</hi> with thy ſelf, what
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169357:17"/> hath been hitherto omitted by thy ſelf, and what by thy Brother <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah Ives,</hi> and hath been publickly Diſputed againſt, as to be of, and from the Devil, and that which hath been ſlighted; undervalued, and Diſputed againſt, and by ſome of thoſe that are now the chiefeſt and the greateſt ſticklers, perſwading perſons to Swear, both in Print, and by Verbal perſwaſions; I ſay, Conſider of things ſeriouſly, in the Fear of the Lord, and the Lord make both <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Them</hi> wiſe.</p>
               <p>In page the ſixth, Thou <hi>crave<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> our <hi>Patience,</hi> whileſt thou <hi>examineſt</hi> the <hi>Grounds</hi> that we who cannot Swear at all, <hi>do bottom upon;</hi> till thou <hi>weigheſt them in the <hi>Ballance</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary;</hi>
                  </hi> And all the <hi>Ballance</hi> that we find thee <hi>weighing them in,</hi> is the <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> the which I have hitherto found, as to thy purpoſe, too light; <hi>yet true as to the ſence of the Letter of the Scripture, as is aforeſaid ſhewed,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> or let your Communication be <hi>wholly or altogether without Oaths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now I ſhall proceed farther by the aſſiſtance of that Spirit, which through mercy I received, <hi>by the Laying on of the Hands of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitery;</hi> Yea, I ſay again, <hi>not by Humane Learning, for I have it not, nor by mine own Wiſdom, which is but fooliſhneſſe,</hi> but <hi>by</hi> the <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> of <hi>that Spirit, which through Mercy I received by the Laying on of the Hands of the Presbitery;</hi> I ſhall take a farther view of thy <hi>account that thou giveſt us of thy work, after thy weighing, and how thou dost apply it,</hi> and <hi>how much it doth amount to,</hi> that ſo thou mayeſt have a <hi>due reward;</hi> for the Labourer is worthy of his hire.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt told us, that the Greek renders, <hi>not at all,</hi> to be wholly, or altogether (as aforeſaid) And now the Application thou makeſt of thy Tranſlation, is this;</p>
               <p>That in the <hi>proper ſence</hi> it ſhould be read, <hi>Swear not <hi>wholly</hi>
                  </hi> or <hi>alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> let not your <hi>Communication be interwoven with Oaths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that thy Speech implies no leſs than this (to wit) <hi>That Goſpel Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples in their Communication, by the allowance of Chriſt, may Swear,</hi> nay, muſt Swear, for that thou bringeſt it to prove, as will be evident anon, though that <hi>Communication</hi> muſt not be <hi>overballanced</hi> with <hi>Oaths,</hi> ſo as that the greateſt part of our <hi>Communication</hi> be <hi>Oaths;</hi> for thy tearms <hi>wholly</hi> and <hi>altogether,</hi> doth admit of ſome Swearing, and that thou doeſt no leſſe then ſay thy ſelf; for theſe terms, <hi>wholly</hi> and <hi>altogether</hi> thou bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in oppoſition to Chriſt words, <hi>Swear not at all, to prove the lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſome Swearing;</hi> ſo that thou ſayeſt, <hi>our Communication ſhould not be interwoven with Oaths,</hi> as much as if thou ſhouldeſt ſay, <hi>every other word, or every other ſentence, ſhould not be an Oath;</hi> yet thy ſpeech is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169357:17"/> as good as if in ſo many words, thou ſhouldeſt ſay, that the verity of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry three or four ſentences, muſt be confirmed with an Oath; or at the leaſt, <hi>ſome Oaths muſt be uſed by the appointment of Christ, for the Confirmation of our Communication;</hi> by which <hi>Tranſlation of thine,</hi> thou wouldeſt <hi>perſwade Goſpel Diſciples,</hi> to be of <hi>another converſation than Chriſt requires they ſhould;</hi> for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Swear not all,</hi> or let your <hi>Communication</hi> be wholly and altogether without Oaths; thou ſayeſt, <hi>talk what you will, but Swear not over much, yet be ſure you Swear in your Communication,</hi> yet let not your <hi>Communication</hi> be <hi>wholly</hi> nor <hi>altogether interwoven with Oaths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now muſt I ſay to thee <hi>Comparatively,</hi> as once the Lord ſpake to <hi>Adam</hi> in the Garden, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.9. and ſay, <hi>Henry Den, where art <hi>thou?</hi>
                  </hi> art thou in and <hi>amongst the Briery Buſhes of Humane Learning,</hi> whilſt thou ſhouldſt be in the <hi>Garden of God, diſcloſing the things of God,</hi> by the <hi>aſſiſtance of the Spirit of God?</hi> Art thou <hi>covering</hi> thy ſelf with the <hi>Fig-leaves</hi> of thine <hi>own Wit,</hi> when thou ſhouldeſt have been <hi>cloathed upon,</hi> with that <hi>cloathing</hi> that is <hi>from Above?</hi> Art thou thus <hi>Goliah</hi>-like, fighting in thine own ſtrength, when the <hi>Lord Chriſt ſaith, That without <hi>Him</hi> thou canſt do nothing,</hi> John 15.9. therefore know, that it is hard to be found fighting againſt God, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.39. What is the cauſe thou art found <hi>aſſerting things thou knowest not how to prove,</hi> for in page the third, thou telleſt us, that to <hi>prevent the impendent evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences neceſſarily following,</hi> of thoſe that <hi>cannot Swear at all,</hi> thou ſhalt <hi>labour to prove</hi> the <hi>lawfulneſſe of an Oath,</hi> in a <hi>Serious</hi> and <hi>Weighty Matter, which cannot otherwiſe be determined;</hi> and yet in concluſion, this <hi>Mountainous</hi> pretence of a <hi>Serious</hi> and <hi>Weighty Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that cannot otherwiſe be determined,</hi> is nothing elſe but a <hi>meer no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of frivolous Communication.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thy <hi>pretence was, to prove that Swearing that was Lawful under the Law, to be Lawful under the Goſpel, in oppoſition to thoſe ſayings of CHRIST,</hi> Mat. 5.34. <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> And <hi>this</hi> thou haſt <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to do,</hi> by <hi>bringing</hi> in <hi>an Exception</hi> to the <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> and <hi>that under a pretence,</hi> that thou hadſt the <hi>Ballance</hi> of the <hi>Sanctuary to try it by;</hi> but <hi>thou</hi> and thy <hi>Ballance</hi> being all weighed in the <hi>true Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance,</hi> thou (as to what thou wouldeſt prove) art <hi>found too light;</hi> but thy tranſlation, to wit, <hi>wholly</hi> and <hi>altogether,</hi> is <hi>found full weight,</hi> and ſuch as in reaſon agreeth with the <hi>Lip of Truth,</hi> which ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> In <hi>oppoſition to whoſe words,</hi> in p. 6. and in p. 7. thou bringeſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Scriptures to <hi>prove</hi> the truth of the <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.7. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.29. the which is a good <hi>evidence for what
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169357:18"/> I ſay,</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Tranſlation</hi> ſpeaketh ſo <hi>much Truth,</hi> and doth <hi>ſo well agree with the Word of Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that inſtead of proving <hi>that SWEARING</hi> to be <hi>Lawful under the GOSPEL,</hi> that was allowed under the Law, thou in ſo many words <hi>endeavoureſt to prove</hi> that <hi>that</hi> Swearing is Lawful, under the Goſpel, <hi>that was never Lawful under the</hi> LAW; for it <hi>was never lawful to Swear in Communication, yet when thou haſt proved what thou canſt prove, it is nothing elſe but Swearing in Communication;</hi> ſo that that Scripture, <hi>Job</hi> 28.2. may be fitly applyed to <hi>Thee,</hi> for <hi>who art thou that dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Counſel by words without knowledge?</hi> yea the counſel of that HOLY CHILD JESUS, <hi>upon whoſe ſhoulders the Government of the Goſpel-Church is, who is that ſame that is Born unto us,</hi> Iſa 9.6. and is called <hi>Wonderful Counſellour,</hi> the <hi>Mighty God,</hi> the <hi>Everlaſting Father,</hi> the <hi>Prince of Peace; who as a Son over his own Houſe,</hi> Heb. 3.6. hath given this <hi>Word of Counſel,</hi> Mat. 5.34. <hi>Swear not at all, <hi>but let your</hi> yea, <hi>be</hi> yea, <hi>and your</hi> nay, nay;</hi> I ſay, notwithſtanding this word <hi>of Counſel,</hi> what he <hi>would not have us to do, and what he would have us to do;</hi> that is, that we ſhould be of a <hi>ſingular Converſation, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> in the <hi>Integrity</hi> of our <hi>Souls,</hi> as in the <hi>preſence</hi> of the <hi>all-ſeeing God,</hi> the <hi>Searcher</hi> of all <hi>Hearts;</hi> So as that we ſhew <hi>forth</hi> his <hi>Praiſe,</hi> and <hi>ſhine</hi> as <hi>Lights</hi> in the <hi>World, adorning</hi> the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by an <hi>Honeſt, Peaceable, Innocent, Quiet, Harmleſſe, True</hi> and <hi>Spotleſſe Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both</hi> in <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Actions;</hi> for our <hi>Converſation as to men,</hi> is <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe</hi> but our <hi>Converſings</hi> with the Sons and Daughters of men, and that is by <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Actions;</hi> and as he requireth our <hi>Actions</hi> ſhould be <hi>Innocent</hi> and <hi>Harmleſſe, True</hi> and without <hi>Fraud;</hi> So alſo our <hi>Tongues</hi> that they <hi>ſpeak Truth, without either Swearing or Forſwearing, truly and without guile:</hi> A part of which <hi>Counſel</hi> thou endeavoureſt to <hi>darken, by thy deep Learning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The which, that thou mayeſt the <hi>better effect,</hi> thou telleſt us, that thou haſt <hi>one thing more</hi> to <hi>add</hi> to <hi>help thee,</hi> which is, That it is <hi>conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded</hi> by the <hi>Antients,</hi> that the <hi>Goſpel of Matthew,</hi> was written in the <hi>Hebrew Tongue,</hi> as <hi>Hierom,</hi> more then <hi>Ten Times,</hi> and <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſaith the ſame, that he wrote his <hi>Goſpel in his own Country Language,</hi> and he cites the ſame out of <hi>Papia,</hi> Saint <hi>Johns Auditor,</hi> and out of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias,</hi> who was the <hi>Scholar</hi> of <hi>Policarpus,</hi> who was the <hi>Scholar</hi> of Saint <hi>John,</hi> and the <hi>rest</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles;</hi> alſo telling to us, that thou haſt <hi>many other Witneſſes; <hi>ſaying,</hi>
                  </hi> that thou haſt <hi>conſulted the Hebrew Copy,</hi> which thou haſt received from the hands of <hi>Sebaſtian Munſter,</hi> which he <hi>reſcued</hi> out of the Hands of the JEWS: <hi>I could wiſh thou
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169357:18"/> wouldest ſtick to ſomething, that ſo I might know where to find thee: first,</hi> thou telleſt us that the <hi>Greek is the true Tranſlation, and anon the Hebrew; one time</hi> this is <hi>an Oath,</hi> and anon <hi>that which was an Oath, is now ſomething equivolent</hi> to an Oath; now thou wilt ſhew us this, then that is the way, now thou art up, then thou art down; and <hi>thus</hi> when thou haſt pleaded for the <hi>Greek, <hi>then thou telleſt us,</hi>
                  </hi> that the <hi>Hebrew <hi>renders it, Swear not in every way,</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>that</hi> is the <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſwer, If it <hi>were found</hi> in the <hi>Greek,</hi> then <hi>not</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> if in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> then <hi>not</hi> in the <hi>Greek;</hi> and upon this account thou tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt us, that our <hi>firſt Pillar</hi> ſtands upon a <hi>doubtful,</hi> nay, upon an <hi>unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable Interpretation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But <hi>Henry Den,</hi> I ſhall follow Thee and Thy <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not but in <hi>concluſion,</hi> by the <hi>aſſistance of that Spirit,</hi> that <hi>produced</hi> a <hi>Glorious Fabrick,</hi> out of that firſt <hi>confuſed Lump, Gen.</hi> 1. to make <hi>Truth ſo appear</hi> in the behalf of him, <hi>who is the <hi>Way,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi>
                  </hi> and <hi>the <hi>Life,</hi>
                  </hi> as that God ſhall have his <hi>Glory,</hi> and <hi>miſled Souls the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit, even to thy ſmiting upon the Thigh,</hi> and ſaying, <hi>What have I done?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> rendreth the ſaying of the Lord Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. <hi>Swear not in every way;</hi> though our Tranſlation ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all;</hi> as if there were <hi>much contradiction</hi> in the terms, and that the <hi>ſence</hi> were <hi>ſomething elſe</hi> then what the <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Scripture holdeth forth;</hi> the Letter of the Scripture, ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> and thy Tranſlation ſaith, <hi>Swear not in every way,</hi> as if he had ſaid, in <hi>every way avoid Swearing,</hi> &amp; what difference that is, that is material, between <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> and in <hi>every way avoid Swearing;</hi> for mine own part, I muſt leave to the <hi>conſideration</hi> of <hi>wiſer Heads</hi> than <hi>mine</hi> to <hi>diſtinguiſh;</hi> And if the Lord Chriſt had ſaid, <hi>It hath been ſaid to them of old time, Thou ſhalt not Forſwear thy ſelf;</hi> but I ſay unto you, <hi>In every way avoid Swearing;</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it had not been as good a Warrant for us to avoid Oaths, as when he ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all?</hi> I ſhall leave the Rational to judge; And what Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <hi>H. Den</hi> had to make ſo much ado about the <hi>Greek</hi> &amp; <hi>Hebrew Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation,</hi> I know not, unleſſe it were to let the World know, that he is a <hi>Greek</hi> and an <hi>Hebrew Scholar:</hi> And therefore, according to the <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon courſe of the World, you muſt believe it, becauſe a deep Learned Scholar,</hi> one that is well read in the <hi>Original Tongues, ſaid it; If this be thy end</hi> Henry Den, why thou haſt manifeſted thy Schollar-ſhip, <hi>and to ſo little purpoſe,</hi> I muſt tell thee, that I find that in this caſe, that <hi>Propheſie</hi> of <hi>Iſaiah</hi> repeated by our Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.19. <hi>is made good,</hi> where the Lord ſaith, <hi>I will deſtroy the Wiſdom of the Wiſe, and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169357:19"/> bring to naught the underſtanding of the Prudent;</hi> and as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes;</hi> ſo thou <hi>reſiſting</hi> the <hi>Truth, ſhall proceed no farther, but ſhall be manifeſted,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas in page 7. and 8. as to our ſecond ground drawn from, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.12. thou telleſt us, that thou wilt <hi>appeal</hi> to the <hi>Judgement of any Rational man, skilful</hi> or <hi>unskilful</hi> in the Languages, whether this hath the ſound of the true interpretation or not, <hi>Above all things my Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, Swear not;</hi> for ſayeſt thou in page 8. <hi>Is it worſe to Swear, the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to commit Adultery, to kill the King, our Political Father, or our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Mother?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>From whence ſome do Infer, that thoſe that are now Impriſoned (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcandalouſly Printed to Publick view as Traytors) who cannot Swear at all, are ſuch as are Guilty of the late Kings Blood, and moſt abominable in other actings alſo; and this ſeemingly Charged upon them by thy ſelf, as if thou dideſt know ſome of them guilty of ſuch things:</hi> But I hope, the all-ſeeing God, the ſearcher of all Hearts, in his own due time will <hi>clear our Innocency,</hi> as to what is <hi>gathered</hi> from thy <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsions,</hi> and <hi>otherwiſe alſo in Print Publiſhed;</hi> And in the mean time, I muſt let thee know, that it had been good <hi>for thee</hi> to have <hi>waſhed thine own hands in innocency,</hi> and that thou hadſt taken a <hi>review of thy <hi>Burford Actings,</hi>
                  </hi> in <hi>order thereunto, before</hi> thou hadeſt ſo <hi>charged o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</hi> yet if thou or any one elſe can juſtly charge us for <hi>thoſe,</hi> or <hi>any other Miſdemeanours;</hi> I ſhall for mine own part crave no other favour at Thine or Their Hands, but that They or Thou, ſee <hi>Condign Puniſhments</hi> be <hi>ſpeedily executed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time, I ſhall by <hi>Divine Aſsiſtance,</hi> conſider of an Anſwer to what thou haſt to ſay to <hi>Jam.</hi> 5 12. as to the Tranſlation, for thou telleſt us, that thou haſt ſomething againſt this <hi>Tranſlation</hi> alſo; and thus thou art <hi>running</hi> in <hi>Romes Road,</hi> for it is and hath been the practice of her <hi>Jeſuitical Prieſts,</hi> and of the <hi>Prieſthood of her Daughter,</hi> to tell the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ity,</hi> as they call us, that we are <hi>Ignorant</hi> of the <hi>Original,</hi> and yet <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf in this, is honeſter than thy ſelf; for as to <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. the <hi>Rhemiſt</hi> Teſtament renders it, <hi>But I ſay unto you, not to Swear at all;</hi> upon which Text in their Annotations, they ſay thus;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> here, not following the <hi>Churches Judgment,</hi> but the bare Letter (as other Hereticks in other Caſes) hold that there is a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Oath lawful, no not before a</hi> Judge, <hi>whereas Chriſt ſpeaketh againſt, ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h and uſual Swearing in common talk, when there is no cauſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whence I would briefly note theſe four things, Firſt, That the <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt Tranſlation,</hi> as to <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. <hi>is the ſame with ours,</hi> and that <hi>they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169357:19"/> quarrel not with the Tranſlation,</hi> to <hi>make us believe that ſomething elſe is meant by the Original.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſecondly, That it is evident, that in the Primitive times, it was the <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> as they call us, from this Text, to judge and hold all <hi>Oaths utterly unlawful in all Caſes:</hi> So that it is evident, by their ſhewing, whoſe <hi>Tranſlation</hi> (as they ſay) was never <hi>adulterated:</hi> I ſay it is evident by their ſhewing, that as to <hi>Oaths,</hi> we <hi>follow</hi> the <hi>Flock of God gone before;</hi> and not only in this, but alſo from <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.39. That it was the <hi>Principle</hi> of this ſort of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>not to reſiſt the Turk,</hi> becauſe the Text ſaid, <hi>But I ſay unto you, Reſiſt not evil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thirdly, That they in their Marginal <hi>Annotations,</hi> can plead no <hi>good Warrant from Scripture,</hi> to <hi>diſprove</hi> or <hi>confute</hi> our <hi>Opinion herein;</hi> but only the <hi>Iudgment</hi> of the <hi>Church;</hi> and how corrupt ſhe is in her <hi>Judgment,</hi> being the <hi>Mother of Harlots and all Abominations,</hi> I ſhall leave thoſe that ſprang from her to judge: And if ſhe were not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, <hi>why ſhould we be Impriſoned for refuſing to Swear againſt her, when it was <hi>never</hi> our Judgments to Swear at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Fourthly, I would here have all to take notice, That the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> or <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> as they are <hi>abuſively</hi> called, are not of ſuch a late beginning and riſe, as the Church of <hi>England</hi> would perſwade men they are; for this that I cite out of the Margent of the <hi>Rhemiſt Teſtament,</hi> was in being a long time before the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> knew her ſelf, even whilſt ſhe was in the Arms, and ſucking the Breaſts of her Adulterous <hi>Mother,</hi> that <hi>SCARLET WHORE.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſee thou findeſt fault with us, and <hi>condemneſt</hi> our <hi>Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> when <hi>ROMES Prieſthood</hi> will not do it; yet this is <hi>Common</hi> with <hi>Book-learned men,</hi> generally in all Ages, that when perſons are either deſirous to <hi>Regulate</hi> according to the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> as to there <hi>Principles,</hi> in <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> then they are <hi>branded</hi> with <hi>ignorance</hi> of the <hi>Original;</hi> and although the <hi>Original</hi> differ not in the ſence in the leaſt, as in thy Exceptions to <hi>James</hi> 5.12. Thou ſaiſt the <hi>Greek</hi> Rendreth it, <hi>Before all things;</hi> where our <hi>Tranſlation</hi> rendreth it, <hi>Above all things Swear not:</hi> And here thou makeſt much ado, as if there were ſuch a vaſt difference between the two Words, <hi>ABOVE,</hi> and <hi>BE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORE,</hi> as that it were a thing impoſſible to think, that they could be reconciled, ſo as to ſpeak to one and the ſame ſenſe. And to this purpoſe thou telleſt us who are thy Authors, as the <hi>Vulgar, Eraſmus,</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> in the <hi>Latine Tranſlations,</hi> who <hi>do all agree</hi> to <hi>tranſlate</hi> it, <hi>ANTE OMNIA;</hi> together with comparing of o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her Scriptures, where the ſame Phraſe is uſed, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.7. <hi>Who were in Chriſt <hi>before</hi> me.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:169357:20"/>
               <p>To the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of which <hi>Scripture,</hi> I ſhall ſay ſomething hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and let thee know, that herein thou dealeſt <hi>unfaithfully with us;</hi> And were it ſo, that we were not <hi>aſſiſted</hi> from <hi>above,</hi> to <hi>diſcover</hi> thy <hi>nakedneſs</hi> herein, thy <hi>nakedneſs</hi> might <hi>become</hi> our <hi>Blindneſs;</hi> and ſo we might <hi>go multitudes of us halting out of Gods way</hi> into the <hi>by-paths of Error.</hi> But to anſwer thee in plainneſs of ſpeech, I muſt let thee know, that as to all that thou bringeſt in thy <hi>former Exceptions,</hi> ſo likewiſe to this, that it is to <hi>very little purpoſe,</hi> and is inſufficient to make our <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation</hi> any other <hi>Senſe</hi> than <hi>what it is:</hi> So that if I make thy <hi>Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> ſpeak the Language of our <hi>Scripture,</hi> without <hi>wronging it;</hi> then it is all one with the <hi>Scripure;</hi> and <hi>then</hi> thou haſt nothing againſt our <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> to weaken our <hi>Pillar,</hi> or to make voyd that <hi>Law,</hi> neither of the Lord Chriſt, nor his faithful Servant <hi>James,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>Swear not,</hi> and <hi>Swear not at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thou telleſt us, that the <hi>Greek</hi> renders it as doth the <hi>Latine, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things:</hi>
                  </hi> And that I may make ſuch a <hi>Diſtinction,</hi> that may be ſatisfactory to the <hi>meaneſt Capacity,</hi> I ſhall let thee know, that <hi>both theſe Words,</hi> have each of them <hi>ſeveral Acceptations</hi> in Scripture, and both of them to one and the ſame Senſes, and both one in the Text; as, Firſt, the Word <hi>BEFORE,</hi> it is uſed in a threefold Senſe: And to bring all theſe <hi>Senſes</hi> for one and the ſame end, becauſe they are ſpoken in one and the ſame words, will prove <hi>Senſeleſs,</hi> as thou doſt <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.7. to prove thy <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> as I ſhall ſhew: Therefore know; that,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Before,</hi> is uſed with reſpect to <hi>Time.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Before,</hi> is uſed with reſpect to <hi>Place.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Before,</hi> is uſed with reſpect to <hi>Eſtimation</hi> or <hi>Superiority.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>As, 1. <hi>Before</hi> is uſed with reſpect to <hi>Time.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom. 16.7.</hi> Salute <hi>Andronicus</hi> and <hi>Junia,</hi> my Kinſmen, and my fellow Priſoners, who are of note among the Apoſtles, who were in Chriſt <hi>firſt, or <hi>before</hi>
                  </hi> me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 1.13.</hi> Who was <hi>before</hi> a Blaſphemer, and a Perſecutor, and Injurious, <hi>&amp;c. Gal. 5.21.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jude 4.</hi> For there are certain men crept in unawares, who were <hi>before</hi> of old Ordained to this Condemnation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>2. <hi>Before</hi> is uſed with reſpect to <hi>Place.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Revel. 14.3.</hi> And they ſang as it were a new ſong <hi>before</hi> the Throne, and <hi>before</hi> the Lamb.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Revel. 7.15.</hi> Therefore are they <hi>before</hi> the Throne of God.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts 5.27.</hi> And when they had brought them, they ſet them <hi>before</hi> the Council.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:169357:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>3. With reſpect to</hi> Eſtimation <hi>or</hi> Superiority; <hi>which is the</hi> ſenſe ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of in the Text, <hi>James 5.12. <hi>Above,</hi>
                  </hi> or <hi>Before</hi> all things my Brethren, Swear not, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>John 1.15.</hi> He that cometh after me, is preferred <hi>before</hi> me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John 1.17.</hi> He it is who coming after me, is preferred <hi>before</hi> me, whoſe ſhoe latchets I am not worthy to unlooſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exod. 20.3.</hi> Thou ſhalt have none other Gods <hi>before</hi> me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And Secondly, the word</hi> ABOVE, <hi>hath a fourfold</hi> Acceptation; <hi>As,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Above, <hi>with reſpect to</hi> Time.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>2.</hi> Above, <hi>with reſpect to</hi> Quantity.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>3.</hi> Above, <hi>with reſpect to</hi> Place.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>4.</hi> Above, <hi>with reſpect to</hi> Eſtimation <hi>or</hi> Superiority.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>1. <hi>Above,</hi> with reſpect to <hi>Time.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 12.2.</hi> I knew a man <hi>above</hi> fourteen years ago, whether in the Body I cannot tell, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acts 4.22.</hi> And the man was <hi>above</hi> forty years old, on whom the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of Healing was ſhewed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rom. 15.6.</hi> Afterwards he was ſeen of <hi>above <hi>500.</hi>
                  </hi> Brethren at once.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>2. <hi>Above</hi> with reſpect to <hi>Quantity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 12.7.</hi> Leſt I ſhould be exalted <hi>above, (<hi>or</hi>
                  </hi> beyond) meaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 11.23.</hi> — In ſtripes <hi>above (<hi>or</hi>
                  </hi> beyond) meaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>2 Cor. 1.8.</hi> — Preſſed out of meaſure <hi>above</hi> ſtrength.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>3. <hi>Above,</hi> with reſpect to <hi>Place.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>James 1.17.</hi> Every good and perfect gift is from <hi>above,</hi> and cometh down from the Father of Lights.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James 3.15.</hi> This Wiſdom deſcendeth not from <hi>above,</hi> but is earthly devilliſh, ſenſual.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Col. 3.1.</hi> If ye be riſen with Chriſt, ſeek thoſe things that are <hi>above,</hi> where Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of the Father.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>4. <hi>Above,</hi> with reſpect to <hi>Eſtimation</hi> or <hi>Superiority.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And this is the <hi>ſenſe</hi> that is ſpoken of in our Text of <hi>James</hi> 5.12. And therefore I ſhall deſire that it be well minded, becauſe it is that which will clear the Text from all doubts, and anſwer thy Objection, and make <hi>thy Tranſlation</hi> ſpeak <hi>our Scripture-language:</hi> for <hi>Above</hi> and <hi>Before</hi> being taken in the ſame ſenſe, with reſpect to <hi>Eſtimation,</hi> is one and the ſame: And where it is read <hi>above,</hi> it may as well be read <hi>before;</hi> and where it is read <hi>before,</hi> it may as well be read <hi>above.</hi> As for Example,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> 1.15. <hi>He that cometh after me is preferred before me,</hi> or, he ſhall be <hi>eſteemed above me.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:169357:21"/>
               <p>Exod. 20.3. <hi>Thou ſhalt have none other gods <hi>before me,</hi>
                  </hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at thou ſhalt eſteem <hi>above</hi> me, or ſet over me as my <hi>ſuperiour,</hi> to have him in <hi>eſtimation above me:</hi> Therefore I ſhall read theſe two Scriptures in <hi>both terms,</hi> the which will produce <hi>but one ſenſe;</hi> and then the Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Tranſlation will prove as light, as thoſe that were brought to <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.34. <hi>Swear not <hi>wholly, altogether,</hi> or <hi>not at all.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Above</hi> (or <hi>before) <hi>all things, have fervent Charity.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.4. Who <hi>oppoſeth himſelf <hi>above</hi>
                  </hi> (or <hi>before) <hi>all that is called of God.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>3 <hi>John</hi> 2. <hi>I wiſh <hi>above</hi>
                  </hi> (or <hi>before) <hi>all things.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9. <hi>God hath highly exalted him, and hath given him a Name <hi>above</hi>
                  </hi> (or <hi>before) <hi>every name.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.10. <hi>Her praiſe is far <hi>above</hi>
                  </hi> (or <hi>before) <hi>Rubies.</hi>
                  </hi> And in our Text the ſenſe ſtands good.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James</hi> 5.12. <hi>Above</hi> (or <hi>before) <hi>all thinge, my Brethren, ſwear not.</hi>
                  </hi> So that the ſenſe that thou bringeſt to find fault with our Text, is that which ſpeaketh the very language of our Text, nothing differing from it in the leaſt. And whereas thou telleſt us, that thou doſt the rather believe this Tranſlation <hi>before all,</hi> to be true, is, becauſe thou haſt compared it with other Texts, where the ſame phraſe is uſed, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.7. <hi>Which were in Chriſt <hi>before</hi> me.</hi> And <hi>Col.</hi> 1.17. <hi>He is <hi>before</hi> all things:</hi> The which can neither of them be fitly applyed to our Text, <hi>James</hi> 5. for theſe Texts do both refer to <hi>Time,</hi> and not to <hi>Eſtimation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But a little to ſhew thee thy folly herein. Suppoſe <hi>Henry Den, Jer. Ives,</hi> and <hi>Henry Adis,</hi> take a Journey from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>York;</hi> and <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Den</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> come into <hi>York <hi>before</hi> Henry Adis;</hi> ſure I am <hi>Henry Den</hi> will come <hi>behind</hi> (as to his end) if he ſhall think to make any rational man believe, that if <hi>Henry Adis</hi> doth prefer Jeſus Chriſt <hi>above</hi> or <hi>before John the Baptiſt,</hi> that theſe two <hi>befores</hi> can be brought to one and the ſame; for then we muſt read the former ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal thus: <hi>Henry Den</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> came into <hi>York <hi>above</hi> Henry Adis;</hi> the which to ſay is <hi>meer nonſenſe:</hi> And yet this is <hi>nothing leſs</hi> then what <hi>Henry Den</hi> in effect <hi>doth aſſert;</hi> for <hi>Henry Den</hi> bringeth a <hi>Before</hi> which <hi>reſpecteth Time,</hi> to diſprove our <hi>Above,</hi> which <hi>reſpecteth not Time</hi> but <hi>Eſtimation;</hi> but <hi>Henry Den</hi> may plainly ſee, that if he had brought a <hi>Before,</hi> which reſpecteth <hi>Eſtimation,</hi> he would then have read our Text, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.12. as doth the <hi>Rhemiſt TESTAMENT,</hi> which readeth thus, <hi>Before all things my Brethren, Swear not;</hi> which is <hi>Henry Den's own Language,</hi> without any <hi>contradiction in the leaſt:</hi> And what need then all this ado about the <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> as if the <hi>Tranſlation</hi> did ſo <hi>much alter the ſenſe of the Text,</hi> as if it <hi>ſhould or did
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169357:21"/> 
                     <hi>alter</hi> the <hi>thing in ended,</hi>
                  </hi> which the Spirit of God layes down as a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition, <hi>Swear not,</hi>
                  </hi> ſo as to be a <hi>poſſitive command, <hi>ye ſhall Swear,</hi>
                  </hi> for <hi>that is the thing Henry Den</hi> intended to beget us to a belief of; for he <hi>quarrelleth</hi> with the <hi>Tranſlation, for no other end, but to prove ſome Swearing in Communication Lawful,</hi> but not <hi>ſo much</hi> as to have our <hi>Communication interwoven with Oaths,</hi> as in page 6. line 26. is evident, which is to prove that <hi>Lawful under the Goſpel, which was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver lawful under the Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that <hi>Henry Den,</hi> I ſee any thing will ſerve turn to patch up thy Opinion, bare Terms, or words without diſtinctions, the which when men uſe <hi>to darken the Counſel of God,</hi> they run into <hi>Confuſion</hi> as thou doeſt, who by thy Scholarſhip would make us believe that ſome <hi>Swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> is lawful under the Goſpel; but I plainly ſee the good Word of the Lord made good, which ſaith, <hi>he taketh the <hi>Wiſe</hi> in his own <hi>Crafti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi>
                  </hi> and thus <hi>the Counſel of the Froward is carried headlong, they walk in darkneſſe in the day time, and grope at none-day, as in the night,</hi> Job 5.13.14. <hi>The Wiſdom of</hi> the (Humane Learned) <hi>Wiſe, is brought to nothing,</hi> and the <hi>underſtanding of the Prudent men, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come folly; for God hath choſen the Fooliſh, the Weak baſe things, and things that are not, to bring to naught the things that are: and his end in all</hi> this, is, that <hi>no Fleſhly, Carnal, Humane Learned Perſons, ſhould Glory in his Preſence,</hi> that ſo his <hi>Son,</hi> and his <hi>Spirit alone may be exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, being manifeſt in the weakneſs of his People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And whereas thou telleſt us in thy laſt page, <hi>That all theſe things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, the Ground appears not ſo ſure, as it was Fancied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To which I Anſwer, That the <hi>Ground</hi> yet, through Mercy, <hi>standeth firm,</hi> and thoſe Objections, the <hi>Pillars</hi> thou ſpeakeſt of, in page. 3. the which in page 6. thou nameſt to be <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. and <hi>James</hi> 5.12. are yet as firm as ever, and are as ſo many <hi>STANDING MON<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENTS in the <hi>houſe</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f God, which is the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Living</hi> God, that <hi>Ground</hi> and <hi>Pillar</hi> of <hi>Truth;</hi>
                  </hi> notwithſtanding thy <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Workman-ſhip,</hi> with thy <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew <hi>Tranſlations,</hi>
                  </hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the help of thy Brother <hi>Jeremiah Ives,</hi> who followed thee, and <hi>much mended thy work too, yet all in vain,</hi> for he was but a <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> at the <hi>work;</hi> and although he formerly had bidden <hi>Defiance</hi> to the Faces of <hi>GENERALS, COLLONELS</hi> and <hi>COMMANDERS in open Field,</hi> in the behalf of his late Maſters, probably to the <hi>gaining of that, which</hi> now <hi>to keep,</hi> he durſt not withſtand the <hi>aſſaults</hi> of a <hi>ſingle MAJOR,</hi> and his <hi>ſmall company;</hi> and thus <hi>betraying his</hi> truſt in that work, in which he was a <hi>Maſter-Builder, he very then</hi> began
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169357:22"/> this <hi>Trade</hi> of <hi>Undermining,</hi> when he followed Thee, the which although he was ſo forward to undertake, yet he had needed, <hi>both He</hi> and <hi>Thy ſelf too,</hi> to have gone to the <hi>Univerſity</hi> again, to have ſtudied to <hi>diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between things that differ;</hi> for taking a <hi>Vow,</hi> a <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> an <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeveration,</hi> and an <hi>Adjuration <hi>for an Oath,</hi>
                  </hi> you run <hi>Babel-Builders-like,</hi> into a <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and ſo may pull an old houſe on your heads in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, <hi>Samſon-like, Judg.</hi> 16. probably to the <hi>wounding and ſlaying thouſands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for <hi>Sophiſtical, Syllogiſtical Science,</hi> that your fore-runner, the <hi>Captain</hi> of your <hi>Work, John Tombs,</hi> as blind as your ſelves in diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, hath been <hi>hewing</hi> theſe <hi>Pillars</hi> withal, yet the <hi>Foundation</hi> is not moved, for it was <hi>Emanuel</hi> that <hi>God-mans</hi> work, to raiſe them, and he muſt be more then a man that can pull them down.</p>
               <p>And whereas thou telleſt us, that the <hi>ground <hi>is not ſo ſure as it was</hi> fancied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Anſwer, <hi>That in pretending to ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke the Foundations, thou haſt had many <hi>Fancies,</hi> for that thou haſt</hi> done, is <hi>meer Fancie,</hi> and that which never <hi>grew in <hi>Truths Garden,</hi>
                  </hi> the <hi>Holy Scrip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ures,</hi> but was fetched out of the <hi>muddy Channels</hi> of <hi>Humane Learning;</hi> and whereas thou telleſt us, that if the Quaker ſaith, <hi>the Light within forbideth him to Swear,</hi> the <hi>conſent of Nations,</hi> thou ſayeſt, <hi>confuteth him:</hi> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving already to thy Conſent of <hi>Nations,</hi> ſaid ſo much as I have, I ſhall leave that QUAKER, that I heard is anſwering thy <hi>Letter,</hi> to anſwer for himſelf, and his <hi>Light within,</hi> and ſhall onely anſwer for my ſelf, and in the behalf of thoſe that <hi>plead Scripture for their Warrant,</hi> which thou ſayeſt is ſo weak; and ſhall let thee know, that ordinary Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar School-boys can tell us, that as there is <hi>weak</hi> and <hi>weaker,</hi> ſo there is alſo <hi>weakeſt of all;</hi> even ſo there are three that have born Teſtimony againſt this Truth, <hi>John Tombs, Jeremiah Ives,</hi> and <hi>HENRY DEN,</hi> and therefore I muſt continue my Speech to thee, and in thine own fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing words ſhall ſay, <hi>Beware you that have ſo done, lest ye hear, <hi>who hath required theſe things at your hands?</hi>
                  </hi> they are thine own words, make the beſt uſe of them thou canſt; it is a good caution, <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, cure thy ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I ſhall farther ſay, as thou ſayeſt, <hi>That Chriſt forbideth all thoſe Exorbitant and <hi>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ravagant Oaths,</hi> whereof now the Streets and Houſes are full; a ſad preſage of ſome Judgement at hand; it was hoped by ſome that the Kings Proclamation, would h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve reſtrained ſuch Debauchery; but alas it is not ſo!</hi> but had the <hi>Fiery Zealous Mayor of London,</hi> and his <hi>Officers,</hi> with the <hi>Iuſtices</hi> of <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce,</hi> of the <hi>City</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:169357:22"/> and <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Weſtmniſter,</hi> and the <hi>Out-Pariſhes,</hi> with them of the ſeveral <hi>Shires</hi> and <hi>Counties,</hi> been but half as careful to have put the Penalty of that Proclamation into <hi>Execution,</hi> and have followed it to the <hi>height,</hi> as they have done the <hi>Obſervation <hi>of that</hi> Proclamation, for ſhutting up the Peaceable, Innocent, Harmleſſe Meetings of us, the Deſpiſed Abuſed Baptiſts;</hi> and in their ſo <hi>Eager</hi> and <hi>Inhumane <hi>Committing us to Priſon,</hi>
                  </hi> even to the Ruine of our Families, unleſſe we who are in the <hi>Gate-Houſe Priſon,</hi> be willing to pay <hi>Traytors Fees;</hi> I ſay, If the <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Iuſtices</hi> as <hi>aforeſaid, had been but as <hi>Zealous for Gods Glory,</hi>
                  </hi> the <hi>Goo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Tranquility</hi> of his <hi>People,</hi> the <hi>Benefit</hi> of <hi>Sinking Souls,</hi> the <hi>Reſtraining</hi> of <hi>Rude, Ranting Revilers,</hi> to the <hi>Converſion</hi> of them, and the many <hi>Lewd</hi> and <hi>Laſcivious Lazy Perſons, Harboured</hi> and <hi>Foſtered up in that Multitude of Dammy</hi> and <hi>Debauched Bawdy houſes,</hi> in and about the <hi>Cities</hi> of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and elſe where, they would then have filled the <hi>Priſons</hi> fuller <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen they be, and upon a far better account than now they are; in which they would have proved themſelves <hi>far better Friends to their <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> to the laſting fame of themſelves and their Poſterity,</hi> to the nouriſhment of <hi>that</hi> and <hi>thoſe,</hi> that are an <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> a <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> and a <hi>Safety</hi> to a <hi>Nation, People</hi> or <hi>Kingdom,</hi> to the <hi>Diſcountenancing</hi> of <hi>that</hi> which is, hath been, and will be the <hi>downfal of the greateſt in Nations;</hi> and the conſequence of this thing, I do bewail as well as thou; and thus far I can go <hi>hand in hand with thee,</hi> and can further upon this account cry out with thee, and ſay, <hi>What times do we behold! nothing but extreams are preſented to our Eyes and Ears, ſome do little elſe but <hi>Swear,</hi>
                  </hi> whileſt thou (with the reſt of thy Compliers with the Times) lookeſt upon Perſons <hi>truly Conſciencious</hi> of an <hi>Oath,</hi> to be <hi>Vitious;</hi> and whileſt <hi>they</hi> in their <hi>obedience</hi> to Chriſt, <hi>dare not Swear at all,</hi> thou thinkeſt <hi>them evil Doers,</hi> becauſe they do not <hi>Swear e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough,</hi> ranking <hi>them</hi> with, and eſteeming them equal to ſuch as are <hi>Adulterers, Killers of their King</hi> and their <hi>own Parents,</hi> as in thy 8th page, and 4. firſt lines; <hi>and wouldest perſwade them to Swear in their Communication,</hi> as is proved by thine own words.</p>
               <p>And although thou complaineſt in the laſt four or five lines of thy laſt page, <hi>That ſome fill their Mouths with <hi>Direful Execrations,</hi>
                  </hi> upon <hi>every triffle, whileſt others will not yield to <hi>Swear,</hi> when weighty mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vehemently urge them;</hi> And ſo thou endeſt as thou beganneſt; for as here, ſo in page 3. line 5. Thou telleſt us, <hi>That thou wilt Labour to prove to us the Lawfulneſſe of an Oath, in a Serious and Weighty Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which cannot otherwiſe be determined;</hi> when thou in all thy Book
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169357:23"/> haſt not laid us down one <hi>Preſident,</hi> by which we can in the <hi>leaſt</hi> come to <hi>any knowledge,</hi> in what <hi>Serious</hi> or <hi>Weighty Matters Oaths may</hi> or <hi>may not</hi> be <hi>lawful</hi> or <hi>unlawful:</hi> But all that thou haſt done with thy <hi>Scholarſhip,</hi> is but to puzzle Perſons with thy <hi>Tranſlations,</hi> finding fault with ours, that ſo, as other Humane Learned men of our Age, thou, if poſſible, mighteſt perſwade men to hang their Ears at your Lips, or elſe no real Truth is to be attained; and although thou in ſome part of thy Book, findeſt much fault with <hi>Common Debauched Swearing</hi> in <hi>Communication;</hi> yet in the Concluſion, thou haſt proved <hi>nothing elſe to be Lawful, but ſuch Swearing;</hi> for all that thou haſt done in all this thy Diſcourſe, is chiefly and alone to perſwade us to a Belief, that when Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> he <hi>commanded us to Swear in our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication,</hi> for all that flouriſh, that thou makeſt with thoſe Scriptures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1. in page 6. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.7. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.29. in page 7.</p>
               <p>To which I have ſaid nothing particularly, becauſe they are brought onely and alone to prove the Truth of thy <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> and thy <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation</hi> was brought to <hi>prove</hi> the <hi>Lawfulneſſe</hi> of ſome <hi>Swearing,</hi> and that ſome <hi>Swearing</hi> thou <hi>reſtraineſt</hi> in thy Diſcourſe, <hi>onely</hi> and <hi>alone</hi> to a <hi>Lawfulneſſe of Swearing</hi> in <hi>Communication,</hi> as in page 6. line 20. of thy Letter, is evident; and thus in pretending to prove ſome Swearing to be Lawful under the Goſpel, that was <hi>Lawful</hi> under the <hi>Law,</hi> as much as in thee lyeth, thou haſt proved that <hi>that</hi> Swearing is <hi>Lawful under</hi> the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> that <hi>never</hi> was <hi>Lawful under the Law.</hi> And yet thou in page 7. line 35. telleſt us in ſo many words, that our Saviour did <hi>onely endeavour to put a ſtop to common and frequent, light and trivial Swearing;</hi> And therefore I ſhall bring thine own words to evidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy ſelf, which are theſe, page 6. line 33. And ſayeſt thou, <hi>It appeareth to be the aim of our Saviour, not to forbid Solemn Oaths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Magiſtrate, between man and man, upon Grave, Mature Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet thou bringeſt us not one <hi>Preſident</hi> for that appearance, though thou ſayeſt it doth appear, for it appeareth not in the leaſt, but by thy ſo ſaying it doth appear; and till it doth appear by thy better ſtability, that thou haſt an <hi>Infallible Spirit,</hi> and ſuch an <hi>Eſtabliſhing Spirit,</hi> as ſhall make thee appear to be an Aſſertor of <hi>Yea and Amen;</hi> and not of ſuch <hi>Yeas</hi> and <hi>Nays</hi> as thou haſt done; and inſtead of believing thy <hi>pretended Appearances,</hi> I ſhall deſire thee to conſider with thy ſelf ſeriouſly, that if thou hadſt appeared with theſe thy <hi>Yeas</hi> and <hi>Nays</hi> before <hi>Feſtus,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> did, whether he might not upon a <hi>far better account</hi> have ſaid to thee,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169357:23"/> than he did to <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 26.24. Thou art beſides thy ſelf <hi>Henry Den, <hi>too much Learning hath made thee mad?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now, <hi>Henry Den,</hi> ſeeing thou with thy <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Hebrew Tranſlations,</hi> haſt proved as good as <hi>nothing;</hi> nay, I do affirm thou hadſt better have ſaid nothing at all, unleſs thou hadſt proved more than what thou haſt proved; Therefore now be perſwaded to call to thy aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, thy Brother <hi>Jeremiah Ives, John Tombs,</hi> and <hi>Theophilus Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourn;</hi> and for thy better <hi>Illumination</hi> herein, <hi>implore</hi> the help of thoſe <hi>two Seed-plots</hi> of <hi>Learning</hi> and <hi>True Religion, <hi>the two</hi> Eys</hi> of this Land (as ſome call them) <hi>OXFORD</hi> and <hi>CAMBRIDG,</hi> with the <hi>Pupils</hi> and <hi>Tutors, Fellows</hi> and <hi>Maſters,</hi> with all that are in them, and all that proceed from them, whether they be <hi>Lawyers, Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, Phyſicians,</hi> or <hi>Divines,</hi> ſo called, whether <hi>Batchelors</hi> or <hi>Maſters</hi> of <hi>Arts, Doctors, Deans,</hi> or <hi>Chapters, Deacons, Arch-Deacons,</hi> or <hi>Prebands, Biſhops,</hi> or <hi>Arch-Biſhops,</hi> and lay before them thy <hi>Greek Tranſlation, Swear not wholly or altogether,</hi> and thy <hi>Hebrew Tranſlation, <hi>Swear not in every way;</hi>
                  </hi> and Co-operate or work together, and ſee what work you will all make of it, when you ſhall bring, Swear not <hi>wholly</hi> or <hi>altogether,</hi> or <hi>Swear not in every way,</hi> to a Serious and Weighty Matter. As ſuppoſe <hi>Henry Den</hi> lend <hi>Theophilus Brabourn</hi> a 100. pound, for which he giveth him a <hi>Bond,</hi> and <hi>John Doe</hi> and <hi>Jeremiah Ives, Richard Roe</hi> and <hi>Henry Adis,</hi> be <hi>Witneſſes</hi> to that <hi>Bond,</hi> the which we will ſuppoſe <hi>is put in Suit,</hi> and the <hi>Caſe</hi> being before the JUDGE, and the <hi>Declaration</hi> and the <hi>Plea</hi> being both <hi>read,</hi> and the <hi>Jurors Sworn, according to</hi> Henry Dens <hi>Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> to give in their Verdict, <hi>neither wholly, altogether, nor in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way, <hi>according to the Evidence;</hi>
                  </hi> And though <hi>John Doe</hi> and <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah Ives</hi> can and will Swear, and ſuppoſe their hands be upon the <hi>Book,</hi> neither <hi>John Doe</hi> nor <hi>Jeremiah Ives,</hi> can Swear an Oath, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what they pretend; for they muſt not Swear <hi>by the Lord,</hi> as it was under the Law (neither do I believe did <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> ſo Swear) when before that double <hi>Officious <hi>Mayor,</hi>
                  </hi> by virtue of <hi>whoſe</hi> Jehu-<hi>like Zeal, to make the King amends for his <hi>Abingtons haſty Mornings Work,</hi> and that Tender Reſpect he ſhewed to the late KING his FATHER at</hi> Holmby <hi>Houſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, That when <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> was frightned into a perſwaſion to Swear neither <hi>John Doe</hi> nor <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> muſt Swear before the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Judge, <hi>no otherwiſe</hi> but as <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> Sware before that <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious and double-diligent Officer, as aforeſaid, not <hi>by the Lord,</hi> but <hi>by the Contents of that Book,</hi>
                  </hi> yea; even by what was <hi>Contained</hi> in that
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169357:24"/> Book; For this is the Form of the Oath, <hi>You ſhall Swear by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of this Book, to ſpeak the Truth, the whole Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h, and no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hing but the Tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h, ſo help you God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I querie (although I think I need not) becauſe he that perſwaded him to go out of Gods way to <hi>Swear,</hi> could as eaſily perſwade him to go out of Gods Way to Swear by that which is no God; yet I ſhall querie whether <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> did ſo much as open the Book, to ſee whether it was <hi>a Divine Service-Book</hi> (as they call it) or a <hi>Bible,</hi> as it is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally bound with the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Testament,</hi> and the <hi>Apocrypha,</hi> with or without the <hi>Service-Book</hi> as aforeſaid, or the <hi>Singing Pſalms,</hi> Compiled by <hi>Thomas Sternhold, John Hopkins, William Wade,</hi> and others, who were ſaid to be <hi>Muſical Servants</hi> to Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> I ſay, whether all, ſome part, or which part of all theſe <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> Swore by? and whether <hi>Jeremiah Ives</hi> did conſider what a <hi>ſtrong <hi>Oath he took,</hi>
                  </hi> and by <hi>how many Gods he Swore?</hi> And for brevity ſake, we will omit the <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> and begin at <hi>Geneſis,</hi> and conſider that there is a <hi>Serpent</hi> and his <hi>Words,</hi> ſeveral falſe <hi>Heatheniſh Gods,</hi> as <hi>Dagon, Molech, Baal, Aſhtroſh, Chemoth, Rimmon, Diana</hi> of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians,</hi> with ſeveral Great and Mighty Men, as the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>Anack, Goliah, Jepthah, Sampſon;</hi> with many <hi>Giants,</hi> and <hi>ſeveral Kings,</hi> Good and Bad, as <hi>Sihon, Og, Agag, Saul, Agrippa, Herod, Pharaoh, &amp;c.</hi> the Multitude of whoſe <hi>Armies</hi> and <hi>Fighting-men</hi> are innumerable, with the <hi>ſeveral ſorts</hi> of <hi>Birds, Beaſts, Fiſh</hi> and <hi>Fowl,</hi> with many more things of <hi>ſeveral kinds;</hi> with <hi>Herbs, Flowers, Plants</hi> and <hi>Trees,</hi> both <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women, good</hi> and <hi>bad,</hi> with ſeveral Stones, both <hi>Pretious</hi> and <hi>Common,</hi> which are contained in the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> as they are <hi>occaſionally Diſcuſſed of,</hi> by the <hi>Great Iehovah,</hi> his <hi>Holy Prophets,</hi> the <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> for the <hi>Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures</hi> are laid down to us, <hi>Prophetically, Prometically, Typically, Allegorically, Hiſtorically, Parrabolically,</hi> as well as by <hi>Precept</hi> or <hi>Command;</hi> in all which Caſes, all things aforeſaid muſt be named, and yet all <hi>Lawful, Godly,</hi> and of <hi>Chriſtian uſe,</hi> and ſuch as are <hi>well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to God,</hi> and many of them uttered by the <hi>Lord Christ himſelf;</hi> as for <hi>Example,</hi> one had <hi>bought a piece of Land,</hi> and another a <hi>Yoak of Oxen,</hi> and another had <hi>Married a Wife,</hi> and therefore they <hi>could not come to the Supper</hi> ſpoken of; to <hi>what end theſe are ſpoken,</hi> the Rational may Judge, that they were of Singular and Holy uſe; But to <hi>Swear by that Land, that Yoak of Oxen,</hi> or <hi>that Wife,</hi> or <hi>that Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> is as <hi>Prophane,</hi> and as <hi>much forbidden,</hi> as to <hi>Swear by Heaven, or Earth,</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> becauſe it is of ſome other thing; And he
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169357:24"/> that Swears <hi>by the Contents of the Bible,</hi> Swears <hi>by what ever is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in that Book,</hi> and muſt Swear by all things therein, <hi>bad</hi> as well as <hi>good,</hi> as well by the <hi>meaneſt things,</hi> as by the <hi>holy Commands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to our <hi>Suppoſal</hi> as aforeſaid, the <hi>Bond</hi> being before the <hi>Judge,</hi> the <hi>Jurors</hi> are Sworn according to <hi>Henry Den</hi> his <hi>Tranſlations,</hi> neither <hi>Wholly, Altogether,</hi> nor <hi>in every way;</hi> and <hi>John Doe,</hi> and <hi>Jer. Ives,</hi> their hands upon the Book, are Sworn, neither <hi>Wholly, Altogether,</hi> nor (to ſpeak the truth) <hi>in every way;</hi> by what means doth <hi>Henry Den</hi> ſuppoſe by his <hi>Tranſlation</hi> to have his 100 <hi>l.</hi> when neither <hi>Judge</hi> (for him we muſt ſuppoſe alſo to be thus lamely Sworn) I ſay, by what means can <hi>Henry Den</hi> ſuppoſe to have his 100 <hi>l.</hi> by ſuch a <hi>Judge, Jurors,</hi> and <hi>Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes,</hi> who are thus Sworn to <hi>Halves,</hi> neither <hi>Wholly, Altogether,</hi> nor <hi>every way?</hi> But if <hi>Richard Roe</hi> and <hi>Henry Adis,</hi> whoſe <hi>yea</hi> is <hi>yea,</hi> and their <hi>nay nay,</hi> ſhall in the preſence of the great <hi>Jehovah,</hi> according to <hi>Henry Den</hi> his <hi>Tranſlation,</hi> and according to the Senſe of our Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. without Swearing <hi>at all, wholly</hi> and <hi>altogether,</hi> and in <hi>every way,</hi> ſpeak the <hi>Truth,</hi> the whole <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>nothing</hi> but the <hi>Truth</hi> in <hi>every Circumſtance,</hi> both of <hi>time, place,</hi> and <hi>perſon, when, where, who,</hi> and <hi>what;</hi> So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat by <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>Judge, Jurors,</hi> and <hi>Evidence, Henry Den</hi> may expect his 100 <hi>l.</hi> from <hi>Theoplilus Brabourn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here it would be well minded by the <hi>People of God,</hi> that they conſider what they that have <hi>Sworn,</hi> have <hi>Sworn <hi>By</hi>
                  </hi> in ſo <hi>Swearing;</hi> and that they lay all <hi>carnal reaſonings aſide,</hi> and not withſtanding the <hi>Kings Proclamation,</hi> that they ſpeedily <hi>Repair</hi> to their <hi>Respective <hi>Meetings, with all</hi>
                  </hi> the <hi>Members that they poſſibly can get together,</hi> that ſo they may make a <hi>great Outcry to the Lord,</hi> in the behalf of the <hi>King</hi> and his <hi>People,</hi> that ſo God may <hi>paſs by and wink at</hi> theſe <hi>OATHS</hi> of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> and for the time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o come, that it may be ſo much taken <hi>notice of,</hi> as that it be never <hi>acted in</hi> by <hi>any,</hi> as a Sin of <hi>Wilfulneſs,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <hi>him</hi> that ſhall <hi>Adminiſter it,</hi> nor by them to whom it ſhall be <hi>Adminſtred:</hi> And if any men ſhall <hi>oppoſe</hi> you in your <hi>ſo doing,</hi> let them know, that you are going to <hi>pray</hi> to the <hi>great King of Heaven and Earth,</hi> by the help of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> in the <hi>name of King JESUS,</hi> for <hi>King Charles</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> that ſo in the <hi>name of King Jeſus,</hi> God may ſhower <hi>down</hi> his <hi>Bleſſings</hi> upon <hi>King CHARLES the ſecond,</hi> under whom you yet hope to lead a <hi>peaceable, quie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and <hi>godly life,</hi> in <hi>all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs</hi> and <hi>honeſty;</hi> and that God may <hi>enlighten</hi> the <hi>Eyes</hi> of their <hi>Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</hi> in theſe <hi>things,</hi> ſo as that the <hi>Judgments</hi> of God <hi>come not speedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly down upon the Nation</hi> for ſuch <hi>Oaths</hi> as theſe.</p>
               <p>Thus the Lord having given this in by the <hi>Incomings</hi> of his Spirit, I could not chuſe but <hi>lay it down,</hi> that ſo there may be a <hi>Conviction</hi> upon
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169357:25"/> the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of <hi>all</hi> that are <hi>herein guilty,</hi> that ſo they may <hi>go to God</hi> and <hi>beg</hi> his <hi>pardon</hi> for this <hi>Sin of <hi>Ignorance,</hi> Wilfulneſs,</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> what it may be called: And I earneſtly <hi>beg</hi> you who <hi>ever</hi> you are, <hi>into whoſe hands this ſhall come,</hi> that you <hi>Improve the beſt of your Intereſt,</hi> to ſee that this be <hi>brought</hi> to the <hi>Kings <hi>view,</hi>
                  </hi> that ſo at preſent there be ſome <hi>ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Conſideration therein had,</hi> that ſo <hi>Englands <hi>Subjects</hi>
                  </hi> be no longer <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced</hi> to <hi>Swear <hi>hand over head,</hi>
                  </hi> by that which is <hi>not GOD,</hi> to the <hi>enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> of the <hi>Simple</hi> of the Land, to the <hi>pulling down</hi> the heavy <hi>Judgments</hi> of God upon them, for their <hi>Ignorance</hi> in their pretended <hi>acceptable ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> of him, in this pretended <hi>Swearing by his <hi>Name;</hi>
                  </hi> by which means they are <hi>plunged</hi> into a <hi>Gulf</hi> of <hi>abominable <hi>Idolatry,</hi>
                  </hi> for he that ſetteth up a <hi>falſe God to Swear <hi>by,</hi>
                  </hi> is an <hi>Idolater,</hi> for he <hi>preferreth</hi> that <hi>Thing</hi> or <hi>Perſon</hi> he ſo ſetteth up, <hi>before his God,</hi> by whoſe <hi>ſtrength only</hi> he can and muſt expect <hi>power</hi> to <hi>perform</hi> his <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Engagements:</hi> And hence it is that the Lord Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Swear not at all, neither by Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, nor by Earth, nor by Jeruſalem,</hi> becauſe they by their <hi>power</hi> or <hi>ſtrength,</hi> are not able to <hi>give ſtrength</hi> nor ability to <hi>perform;</hi> the which I judge might be <hi>convincing</hi> to any rational man, in reaſon to conclude, that to call God to <hi>Witneſs</hi> a thing, is not to <hi>implore</hi> his <hi>help</hi> to <hi>perform</hi> that <hi>thing;</hi> and to aſſert the certainty of a <hi>thing,</hi> by the certainty of <hi>the Lords living,</hi> is not to crave his <hi>aſſiſtance</hi> in the leaſt to make good that <hi>thing</hi> that is already certain, and therefore not a <hi>Swearing by God</hi> to make good the certainty of what is already certain.</p>
               <p>And therefore I would have <hi>Henry Den, Jer. Ives, John Tombs,</hi> and <hi>Theophilus Brabourn,</hi> know, That their aſſerting, that <hi>Calling God to Witneſs,</hi> is <hi>Swearing,</hi> in the Apoſtles ſaying, <hi>God is my Witneſs,</hi> or <hi>I take God to Record;</hi> or in ſaying, <hi>as the Lord liveth,</hi> or <hi>as the Lord is true:</hi> The which I reſolve, God aſſiſting, to <hi>handle more fully</hi> in my further <hi>Anſwer</hi> to <hi>Theophilus Brabourn</hi> his <hi>Book;</hi> which will <hi>more fully treat the na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ure of an Oath;</hi> and in which will be <hi>contracted that which in this Book lyeth more confuſed and ſcattered;</hi> in which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhall be <hi>more fully,</hi> yet very <hi>briefly Anſwered,</hi> to <hi>John Tombs,</hi> and alſo <hi>Jer. Ives,</hi> although as to the main <hi>Argument</hi> of <hi>Goſpel-Diſciples Swearing,</hi> I have to him <hi>ſaid ſufficient</hi> in my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to <hi>Col.</hi> 2.24. the which had it been here <hi>inſerted,</hi> would have ſwelled to ſomething too <hi>large a Bulk.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus having, by <hi>divine Aſſiſtance,</hi> ſcanned over thy Work <hi>fully</hi> in <hi>every Particular,</hi> and therein in <hi>plainneſs</hi> of <hi>Speech,</hi> according to the <hi>Ability received,</hi> in a meaſure cleared up every thing that may ſeem <hi>Cloudy or dark,</hi> that ſo thou with others maiſt have a clear ſight of <hi>Truth</hi> from <hi>Error</hi> herein; and that <hi>thou</hi> with <hi>others</hi> may <hi>ſay</hi> with <hi>me,</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:169357:25"/> and <hi>ſome others,</hi> as ſaith the Lord Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.34. with another of his faithfull Servants, <hi>James</hi> 5.12. <hi>Swear not,</hi> and <hi>Swear not at all:</hi> And if in what I have ſaid, I have grated ſomething too hard upon thee and the reſt, as to <hi>Humane Learning,</hi> I muſt tell thee, I did it not that I <hi>undervalue Humane Learning,</hi> for I own it in its <hi>place</hi> to be of <hi>ſingular uſe;</hi> neither do I ſo <hi>beat it down,</hi> becauſe I <hi>have it not,</hi> for had I it <hi>my ſelf,</hi> I ſhould with the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in this place, as to the <hi>Things of God, undervalue it,</hi> and come <hi>only</hi> in the <hi>demonſtration</hi> of the <hi>Spirit;</hi> And therefore know, that <hi>what</hi> I have <hi>ſaid</hi> as to <hi>that,</hi> I ſaid it on purpoſe, and in the faithfulneſs of my ſoul for thine, and their good, if poſſible to <hi>beat thee out</hi> of a <hi>Dependancy</hi> upon it, hath ſo thou might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>come out of thy ſelf,</hi> and as I may ſo ſay, to <hi>Plow with Gods Heifer</hi> in the things of God; and uſe <hi>that only</hi> in and about thy <hi>Drugs, Diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and <hi>Chymical Extractions,</hi> and other <hi>ſecular Affairs;</hi> and let that <hi>Doctrine</hi> that thou doſt manage on in that <hi>Society</hi> thou belongeſt to, be only <hi>Compounded</hi> by the <hi>Spirits finger,</hi> whoſe only and alone work will beſt become it.</p>
               <p>And if upon tryal thou find not ſuch a meaſure of it, as may diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to thee the deep things of God, to the ſtopping the mouths of the Gain-ſayers, that thou go to God in his <hi>own Way,</hi> for the attaining of it, <hi>the which for a long time thou haſt rejected;</hi> that ſo thou mayeſt ſpeak and write the things that appertain to ſound <hi>Doctrine,</hi> to the glory of God, the good of Souls, and thine own Eternal well-being:</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Which is the deſire of him, who is willing, according to the Ability received, to ſpend and be ſpent for the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the TRUTH, for the benefit of Souls.</hi> HENRY ADIS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:169357:26"/>
            <head>A WORD to <hi>Theophilus Brabourn.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIEND,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving Read thy Sheet, concerning the <hi>Lawfulneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>Supremacy,</hi> and having a Reſolution to make ſome Anſwer thereunto, I cauſed the Printer to inſert thy name with the reſt, in the Title Page of this my Book, intending to have ſaid ſo much to it, as ſhould have Anſwered the Subſtantial part of it; but it coming not to my hands, till this Anſwer was going to the Preſſe, and finding I had Anſwered much of it, the which being out of my hands, I could not inſert thy name in thoſe parts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I had Anſwered to others in the ſame Caſes; I ſhall there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſire thee to buſie thy ſelf but a little, in order to thy Satisfaction, in what I have ſaid to others of thine own judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, till I procure the Preſſe to go for thy further Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: And ſhall reſt thy Friend, ſo far as thou art a Friend to thy ſelf, in Owning and Standing for Truth, in this Crooked and Adulterous Generation; And ſhall,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Subſcribe my Self therein, Thy FRIEND,</hi> HENRY ADIS.</signed>
               <dateline>From my <hi>Contended Caſtle,</hi> the <hi>Gate-Houſe Dungeon,</hi> till <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Offenders Fees</hi> be mittigated and taken off; my Diſcharge running, <hi>Being found Guiltleſs, pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing due Fees;</hi> which is—</dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
